<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The penitent Christian, fitted with meditations and prayers, for a the devout receiving of the Holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper, / by Lewis Southcomb, rector of Rose-Ash in the county of Devon. ; For the benefit of the people under his charge, and others.</title>
            <author>Southcomb, Lewis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93578</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4751A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184495</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077640</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077640</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151744</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93578)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151744)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2274:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The penitent Christian, fitted with meditations and prayers, for a the devout receiving of the Holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper, / by Lewis Southcomb, rector of Rose-Ash in the county of Devon. ; For the benefit of the people under his charge, and others.</title>
                  <author>Southcomb, Lewis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 148, [7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Royston, bookseller to the King's most Excellent Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisements: [7] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 53 misnumbered as p. 55.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Lambeth Palace Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentence --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151744:1"/>
            <p>THE Penitent Chriſtian, Fitted with <hi>Meditations</hi> and <hi>Prayers,</hi> FOR The Devout Receiving OF THE HOLY SACRAMENT OF THE <hi>Lords Supper,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>LEWIS SO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THCOMB,</hi> Rector of <hi>Roſe-Aſh</hi> in the County of <hi>DEVON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Benefit of the People under his Charge, and Others.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>St.</hi> John <hi>6.56.</hi>
               </bibl> He that eateth my Fleſh, and drinketh my Blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> Bookſeller to the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty, 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:151744:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Inſtitution of his laſt Supper.</head>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Mark.</hi> 14.22.</bibl> 
                     <p>And as they did eat. Ieſus took bread &amp; bleſsed &amp; brake it &amp; gaue to them &amp; ſaid, Take eat, this is my body.</p>
                     <p>And he took y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cup &amp; when he had given thank he gave it to them &amp; they all dranke of it.</p>
                  </q>
                  <figDesc>depiction of Last Supper</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:151744:2"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:151744:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151744:3"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Reverend Father in God, THOMAS Lord Biſhop of <hi>Exon.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT were a piece of very great and intolerable vanity, (which would need a bigger Apology than even the prefixing your Lordſhip's great Name to this mean Diſcourſe) to think, that I could ſay any thing more or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than what has been already ſaid on this Subject: particularly of late years by the Pious and Learned Dr. <hi>Patrick,</hi> in his three ſeveral excellent Treatiſes of the Holy Sacrament. I can therefore truely aſſure your Lordſhip, that I was very far from any ſuch <hi>perſwaſion or thought</hi> in the publiſhing theſe Sheets.
<pb facs="tcp:151744:4"/>The <hi>chief reaſons</hi> that I had to do it were two: <hi>Firſt,</hi> that as this plain Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe was primarily deſign'd only for the <hi>benefit and uſe</hi> of the people of my <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Charge;</hi> ſo are there ſome things in it fitted for their <hi>peculiar needs and tempers:</hi> with which no man can be ſo well acquainted as my ſelf. The other reaſon was, that though I could eaſily have recommended them to very many far better Treatiſes of thoſe holy Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, yet I have obſerv'd, that moſt men are much more ready to <hi>read attentive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſeriouſly conſider</hi> any thing publiſht by a perſon whom they <hi>know,</hi> and with whom they daily <hi>converſe,</hi> (&amp; by whoſe Neighbourhood and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they have contracted a particular <hi>Friendſhip</hi> and <hi>Familiarity</hi> with him, which begets a mutual <hi>confidence</hi> and <hi>endearment</hi>) than they would, a better Diſcourſe of one altogether unknown to them. For their ſakes therefore, chiefly have I adventured it abroad: but if it may be uſeful to any other the meaneſt Soul, in the promoting a more <hi>frequent
<pb facs="tcp:151744:4"/>and Devout uſe</hi> of this deplorably neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected Duty, I ſhall have my deſire and aim. And in proſpect of that end and Deſign, ſhall be content to run the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture of the Cenſures of all men what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. Againſt which, I ſhall be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter guarded, if the many <hi>imperfections</hi> of this Diſcourſe, (particularly it's <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary plainneſs</hi> even to a fault, though in that, it is adjuſted to the <hi>Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities</hi> of them to whom it was firſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and for whom it is principally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) may not hinder your Lordſhips vouchſafing me and it your <hi>Bleſſing</hi> and your <hi>Patronage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot but remember your Lordſhips great earneſtneſs at a late Viſitation, in preſſing us of the Clergy, to recommend a more frequent and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal practiſe of this Duty to our People. And I thank God, this ſmall evidence of my obedience to that injunction, as it brought with it ſome conſiderable ſucceſs to my People, ſo I have great reaſon to believe, that (how mean ſoever it really be) by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it into their hands, it may be
<pb facs="tcp:151744:5"/>greater yet. However ſuch as it is, it is humbly laid at your Lordſhip's Feet, by</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhip's affectionate honourer, and faithfully devoted Servant</hi> Lewis Southcomb.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:151744:5"/>
            <head>To the People of his Charge, the Pariſhioners of <hi>Roſe-Aſh</hi> in the County of <hi>Devon.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Friends and Neighbours,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT has long been my great wonder and trouble too, to ſee ſo many of you who are conſtant frequenters of moſt other publick Offices of the Church, and ſeem to be great Lovers and Friends of it, to be ſo negligent and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in your coming to the Holy Sacrament of the Lord's Supper.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, I have not altogether ſo much reaſon to complain of this now, as I have
<pb facs="tcp:151744:6"/>had heretofore; but however, I am ſure there is yet too much reaſon for ſuch a Complaint as this. That the neceſſity and meaning, the benefits and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of this <hi>Chriſtian Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> ſhould be no better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and conſidered; and the Table of our dear Redeemer ſo unfrequented, deſerves to be bewailed with tears of blood: and there may be reaſon to fear, that the omiſſion of this holy duty is one crying Sin of the Nation.</p>
            <p>The concernment that I ought to have for you, in that Relation which I bear to you, makes me willing to hope, you will no longer be partakers in this too common guilt. What
<pb facs="tcp:151744:6"/>other mens Reaſons for this great Neglect may be, I know not; But I have ſome cauſe to think, that the chief ground of your too ſeldom approaching theſe holy Myſteries is this, <hi>that you are not ſatisfied of your preparations, or not ſufficiently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, wheher your Examination and your Faith, your Repentance, or your Charity</hi> are ſuch as they ought to be, and ſo tremble at the thoughts of unworthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, and are reſolv'd to let it alone, and by ſo doing, at once, rob the Soul of it's great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Priviledge, and higheſt Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. If this be your Caſe, give me leave to enquire, If you were not ſatisfied as to the Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of an <hi>Eſtate,</hi> would
<pb facs="tcp:151744:7"/>you not willingly ask Counſel of the <hi>Lawyer?</hi> or if you were afraid of the State of your <hi>health,</hi> would you not run for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the <hi>Phyſician?</hi> If ſo, let me beſeech you, in matter of doubt or Scruple or diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Conſcience, if you think not fit to adviſe with me, do it with ſome other Miniſter of Religion of greater abilities; and not let your doubts and ſcruples keep you from this <hi>Solemn Act Chriſtian Worſhip,</hi> when you may ſo eaſily have them ſatisfied. The only Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that I can think of, why you ſhould not readily and willingly do ſo, are theſe, Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther firſt, you queſtion <hi>our willingneſs to offer you ſatisfaction</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:151744:7"/>if you come, and that we are loath to be troubled; Or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>you queſtion our ability,</hi> and think you can judge of your own ſtate, as well as a Guide of Souls. Or, thirdly, you cannot <hi>conquer your own loathneſs</hi> and unwillingneſs and fears ſo to do. Or fourthly, you are afraid we would <hi>deſpiſe you</hi> for ſo doing, or make known the <hi>ſecrets</hi> of your Soul.</p>
            <p>To all which therefore I ſhall briefly anſwer.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If you queſtion my <hi>willingneſs</hi> to endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move, and ſatisfie your doubts, or think me unwilling to hear you, and ſuppoſe me loath to be troubled, I do as to this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:151744:8"/>you, that you will find me (by God's aſſiſtance) as ready to endeavour your ſatisfaction, as to take the Tenth of your Poſſeſſions; and as we of the Miniſtry love our <hi>own</hi> eternal Intereſt, ſo we cannot but be concern'd for the future ſafety of <hi>your</hi> Souls, when our neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects would endanger the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of our own.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, it may be 'tis our <hi>ability</hi> you doubt of, and think you can judge of your own State as well as a <hi>Spiritual Guide.</hi> To this I anſwer, that though it may be we are not all <hi>good Lawyers,</hi> or skilful <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians,</hi> or <hi>cunning managers</hi> of our affairs of this World, yet 'tis not to be ſuppoſed but that
<pb facs="tcp:151744:8"/>ſuch who have made it the chief buſineſs of their life, to know the mind and will of God, ſhould at leaſt know ſomewhat more of it than they who have been bred up in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Imployments. Beſides, though you ſhould ſuppoſe us to underſtand but little more of Divine things than your ſelves, yet conſider, few men can ſo well judge of their own ſtate and caſe as another for them. But to put an end to this queſtion, I ſhall for my ſelf declare and promiſe, that if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of your ſcruples of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in this Caſe (or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) ſhould be ſuch, as that you ſhall think my directions not to be ſafe and ſatisfactory,
<pb facs="tcp:151744:9"/>that then, I will undertake, to procure you the opinion of ſome or one of the moſt wiſe, and holy and learned perſons of the Nation without giving you any further trouble.</p>
            <p>But thirdly, it may be you are willing to receive advice and directions in any ſcruples of Conſcience, but you cannot conquer <hi>your own loathneſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs, and ſecret fears,</hi> when you would make them known; If this be your Caſe, I anſwer. Be pleas'd to conſider, what you would do, if you were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in as good earneſt with Almighty God and your Souls, as you are with reſpect to your <hi>Bodies and Eſtates;</hi> and why ſhould it be thought more a
<pb facs="tcp:151744:9"/>ſhame to be concern'd for an immortal Soul than for a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Intereſt? when in truth it will be eſteemed far more creditable and prudent too by all good men? and as for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for ill men, no matter what they ſhall think of you for ſo doing. Nay, as all wiſe and holy men will infallibly reſpect you much the more for ſo doing, ſo alſo all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſort of the World, that outwardly reproach and ſcoff at you for it, will inwardly and really reverence you the more. Beſides, ſit down a little, and when you are next private and alone, conſider ſeriouſly what you would do on a ſick Bed; is not the company of a Guide
<pb facs="tcp:151744:10"/>of Souls welcome then? is not his advice thankfully received, and joyfully purſued, and his prayers for you look't on as the greateſt kindneſs he can do for you? Remember <hi>it will come to this again:</hi> and why then ſhould you not be ready to adviſe with them ſooner as well as later, when they are capable of doing you more good, and you capable to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form more. And would you once but throughly perſwade your ſelves of this as a great trueth, that a pious Perſon would have a much greater value and eſteem for you, for ſuch a care of your Souls, I am apt to think, that then you would as readily apply your
<pb facs="tcp:151744:10"/>ſelves to them in ſuch Caſes, as you would be to make an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous bargain.</p>
            <p>Conſider further, Self-deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al is a great Chriſtian-Duty, (St. <hi>Matt.</hi> 16.24.) and to do <hi>violence</hi> to our ſelves in <hi>conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſubduing that unwillingneſs</hi> that we have to open a doubt or ſcruple of Conſcience to a Miniſter of Religion, would be one great Exerciſe of that Duty.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, poſſibly neither of theſe may be the reaſons, why you will not ask their Counſel or direction; but you are afraid <hi>that we would deſpiſe you for ſo doing, or make known the ſecrets of your Soul.</hi> I anſwer, ſo far ſhould we be from this, that
<pb facs="tcp:151744:11"/>we ſhould look upon them that would ſo do, to have a greater care of, and concernment for their eternal ſafety, than the generality of the World have; we ſhould eſteem you as thoſe that are in good earneſt with God and their Souls; we ſhould from thence have good ground of reaſon to believe, that Religion is the Practice of ſuch, not their Profeſſion only. Nay, we ſhould be apt to hope, that our pains and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours have had ſome ſucceſs with them, and that they are truely willing to be in <hi>ſafety with Jeſus at Jeruſalem,</hi> when they thus are deſirous, that a <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Guide</hi> ſhould take them by the hand, and aſſiſt and direct
<pb facs="tcp:151744:11"/>them in their Journies thither. And then as for your fear that we will <hi>make known the Secrets of your Souls</hi> which you ſhould at any time diſcover to us, this is unreaſonable; for as 'tis high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſingenuous, and unjuſt ſo to do, ſo are we ſtrictly bound by the Canons, (that is, by the wholſome and excellent Laws of the Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 113.</note> which every one of us have engaged to obſerve and obey) to conceal all ſuch caſes; and not at any time to reveal and make known to any perſon whatever, any ſuch truſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to us.</p>
            <p>Having thus taken off your great objection, I ſee nothing more that you can juſtly plead
<pb facs="tcp:151744:12"/>in excuſe for your abſenting your Selves, but what may poſſibly be ſpoken to in the following book.</p>
            <p>If you ſhall not here mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with helps ſufficient to direct you, in the particulars of <hi>Self-Examination,</hi> or in your Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations when you are at the holy Table, that want will be abundantly ſupplied by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther book, I mean, <hi>The whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Duty of Man;</hi> a book, which a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you tender the welfare of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Souls, I deſire no one famil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may be without.</p>
            <p>Two ſorts of perſons the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are among you, which I woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deſire chiefly to read and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this diſcourſe; Firſt, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> who wholly abſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:
<pb facs="tcp:151744:12"/>Secondly, thoſe who though they do not wholly neglect this Duty; yet come to it very ſeldom. <hi>As for them that wholly abſent</hi> themſelves, my buſineſs in theſe Papers, is to invite them earneſtly to fit and prepare their Soul to come and take the very next oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities that ſhall be given them, whatſoever pain or ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial it ſhall coſt them, to put on the Wedding-Garment, leſt all opportunities may ſhortly be at an end and over, and they be found in the day of Judgment, to have lived and dyed in the guilt of this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous neglect. <hi>As for them who ſometimes come, but very rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> my earneſt deſire of them
<pb facs="tcp:151744:13"/>is, to fit and prepare the Sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to come more frequently, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that they may be ſo perſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this frequency, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whenever their Lord ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> come, <hi>he may come and find the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo doing:</hi> At leaſt, that he ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> come, and find in them a So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> habitually diſpoſed for it, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not long before to have bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo doing.</p>
            <p>That the good God of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> infinite mercy may open a your Eyes, to ſee, and with ſerious heart conſider, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and advantages of a fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quent and devout uſe of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> holy Myſteries, is the pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Friend and Servant in our Saviour.</hi> Lewis Southcomb.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151744:13"/>
            <head>OF THE HOLY SACRAMENT OF THE LORDS SUPPER.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>THE firſt great <hi>Infelicity</hi> that befel the World, was the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> by which he loſt Paradiſe, and he and his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity became uncapable of being ſaved by the terms of the <hi>firſt Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi> But the greateſt <hi>Bleſſing</hi> that was ever vouchſaf'd to the Sons of Men, was the coming of our Saviour, to reſtore us the hopeful poſſibilities of Salvation; to eſtabliſh <hi>a new Covenant,</hi> between God and us, and to <hi>ſeal</hi> it by his Blood.</p>
               <p>As in our Baptiſin we were received into this Covenant of Grace and Mercy,
<pb facs="tcp:151744:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151744:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:151744:15"/>ſo have we ſince <hi>ſtained</hi> and <hi>polluted</hi> theſe <hi>white</hi> Robes by unholyneſs and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and broken our part of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. But now that we ſhould refuſe, when we are called and invited, to come <hi>and renew it</hi> in the Holy Sacrament, that we ſhould refuſe to come with the reſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our Brethren, and commemorate the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Love of this our Lord, is equally ſtrange and deplorable.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore upon this conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and becauſe the great <hi>Feſtival</hi> ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part in memory of our Saviour's <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> from the Grave, is at hand, offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you ſome Meditations, touching that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Comfortable, that Divine an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Heavenly action; that ſo we may co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to our Lord, who has already invited u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>willingly and chearfully; faithfully and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably; humbly and penitently; with Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and Devotion;</hi> and be found by him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have that Wedding-Garment on, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> may be accepted by him now, and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> day of Judgment.</p>
               <p>Though there are ſome, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Hammond, <hi>and</hi> Gomar. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero. Synop.</note> great Men, that ſupp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the words of the Text <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not directly and prope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſpoken of the Holy Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, becauſe it <hi>was not then inſtitut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151744:15"/>yet becauſe<note n="*" place="margin">Pro Carne Corpus habet Syrus, quae vox &amp; in Euchar, inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutione legitur, ad quam hic tanta quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam alluſio eſt Grot. in <hi>v. 53.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>others</hi> doubt not but there is a reſpect had to it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhortly after to be inſtituted; and there are<note n="†" place="margin">Luc. Brugenſis Mal. citant Synop.</note> 
                  <hi>ſome</hi> that ſay ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, that it is to be underſtood and meant of the Sacramental eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and a<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> of Religious Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies.</note> great and excellent perſons ſayes, he does not in the leaſt doubt of it. I ſhall not therefore queſtion to underſtand and take the words in the ſame ſence alſo.</p>
               <p>From which I might offer this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</p>
               <p>That worthily, and with a due prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to eat the Fleſh, and drink the Blood of our Saviour, ſhall, by placing him in our heart, and us in his, unite us more cloſely to him; and is an happy earneſt of Eternal Salvation.</p>
               <p>For the Proof and Confirmation of which, I might inſtance, in St. <hi>Jo.</hi> 6.54.57.58. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.17. and many other places of Holy Scripture. But to make the Text more uſeful to our preſent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, I ſhall from it ſpeak to 4 things.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:151744:16"/>
                  <item>Firſt, I ſhall briefly ſhew you, that this is a neceſſary holy and Chriſtian Duty to be frequently performed by us, and the neglect of it infinitely dangerous.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, I ſhall conſider to what end it was inſtituted or appointed by our Bleſſed Saviour.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, Shew how we are to come prepared to partake of theſe holy Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</item>
                  <item>Fourthly and Laſtly, inſiſt upon 4 or 5 Conſiderations after Receiving.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>First, that this is a neceſſary, holy and Chriſtian Duty, to be frequently performed, and the neglect dangerous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For whatever we have an expreſs Command of our Saviour, unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly it requires our <hi>obedience,</hi> and is ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> indiſpenſable <hi>duty,</hi> to be obeyed by un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> readily and willingly, with Sincerity and Conſtancy; And this was one of the laſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> injunctions which our dear Redeemer, a little before his Death was pleas'd to leave with us. <hi>Lu.</hi> 22.19. — <hi>This do i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> remembrance of me.</hi> And that we might have the more full aſſurance of the truth of it, the bleſſed Apoſtle, when he ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of this inſtitution and command of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Saviour, ſayes, I have received of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord, that which I alſo delivered unto
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151744:16"/>you, that <hi>the Lord Jeſus the ſame night in which he was betrayed, took bread, &amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23, 24, 25, 26. — <hi>I have</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>received of the Lord,</hi> as if he had ſaid, though I were not my ſelf preſent, when our Lord ordained and appointed this Memorial of his death and ſuffering, by which we that name his Name, are to ſhew forth his death till he come; yet I do aſſure you,<note place="margin">Grot.</note> that I received it (that is, either by the other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who were both Ear and Eye-witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or by immediate Revelation from Heaven) from our Saviour, that the very ſame Night in which he was betrayed, ſoon after to be buffeted, reviled, ſcourg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſpit on, crucified for our Salvation, that he inſtituted this holy Feaſt, to be continued to the end of the World.</p>
               <p>But then as this is a neceſſary and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Duty, ſo is it to be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not only once in the whole Courſe of our Lives, once in this our preſent State and no more; or once at the hour of Death, as ſome of us are too apt to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and as willing to ſhew by their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; but a holy and heavenly Duty to be performed more <hi>frequently.</hi> And for a Confirmation of this, let us ſee. Firſt, what the holy <hi>Scriptures</hi> ſay to the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151744:17"/>of this action. Secondly, what was the <hi>Practice</hi> and the <hi>Custome</hi> of the firſt Worthies of the Chriſtian <hi>Church,</hi> ſhortly after our Saviour's time. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Lay down ſome <hi>Reaſons</hi> for our fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent attendance on thoſe holy Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
               <p>And if from all theſe we find cauſe for our often Communicating at the Lord's Table; if from Scripture, from the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the firſt and pureſt ages of the Church of Chriſt, and from Reaſon too; then I hope that each ſoul preſent will lay this home to his own heart, and take it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his moſt ſerious conſideration, and then ever for the time to come, endeavour to make up his <hi>former</hi> too <hi>great neglects</hi> by his <hi>future frequency</hi> in this holy Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>Firſt, let us ſee what thoſe Scripture are, that either countenance or imply the frequent performance of this holy acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for this let us conſider <hi>Act.</hi> 2.42. <hi>They continued ſtedfaſtly in the Apostles do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in breaking of bread and prayers.</hi> We read <hi>Act.</hi> 2.7. that on the firſt day of the Week, they uſually came together to break Bread. So alſo 'tis ſaid 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. <hi>Do this as often as ye ſhall drink it is remembrance of me.</hi> The word [ſtedfaſtly]
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151744:17"/>as is obſerved by a<note n="*" place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>P.</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Sacrifice.</note> Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Learned Perſon, denotes the frequency of the action, and the words [as often] may imply it alſo.</p>
               <p>Oh here then before we paſs any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let us ſix our thoughts and conſider, if thoſe who firſt named the Name of Chriſt, <hi>continued</hi> in it ſo <hi>ſtedfaſtly,</hi> if at leaſt on the firſt day of the week, out of their flaming Love and Affection to their dear Lord and Maſter, they remembred his Death with praiſe and thanksgivings; how ill Copiers out of ſo holy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed an <hi>Example</hi> are ſome of us? They were it ſeems ſo <hi>ready</hi> to commemorate their dying Lord, ſo full of Zeal, ſo <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and forward,</hi> to go forth to meet him at his Table; that they ſcarce ever put off their Wedding Garment, but their whole lives were a conſtant and habitual preparation for this holy Feaſt. Whereas in this declining Age of the Goſpel, in which holineſs ſo viſibly decayes, how loath are we to approach him? how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie when we are there? how joyful when we are gone? So unwilling, that alas! we muſt be even hal'd and drag'd to it. And it may be feared, that ſome of us could even wiſh it over, and at an end already.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151744:18"/>
               <p>Why, what's the Reaſon of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs, this backwardneſs, this loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to go to meet the Lord of life in the moſt <hi>holy and ſweet and pleaſant Duty</hi> in the World? Is there ſo much charge, or difficulty in it; or is it ſo hard to be performed? O what is there in this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Action, that any Soul that profeſſes the Religion of the ever Bleſſed Jeſus ſhould have ſuch an averſneſs to it? Say, are there any expenſive <hi>chargeable Sacrifices</hi> to be offered? any <hi>Firſtlings</hi> of our <hi>Flocks</hi> to be ſlain? No, why what's then the Cauſe, that we ſhould not be as ready and forward, and, (when any opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are offered us to remember the death of our Great Maſter in this holy Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) as conſtant too, as the Sun is to run his race? Alas! our great Reaſon is, That the <hi>Wedding-Garment of Religion and Holyneſs, Repentance and Reformation of our Lives, Charity and Devotion</hi> does not pleaſe us; We are loath to put it on, it ſits uneaſie about us: we are hugely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to put off the old <hi>ſpotted rayment</hi> of Sin and Iniquity, of Wrath and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and Irreligion. We find no taſt, no reliſh, in the Sweets and Delicacies of Piety and Vertue.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:151744:18"/>
               <p>We are willing enough doubtleſs to meet our Lord, that is, if we thought he would receive and welcome us, with our ſins about us, and with our old affections to them; then would we continue as ſtedfaſtly in breaking of bread and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as ever the firſt Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies did,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id.</hi> ibid. p. 9.</note> (though it were twice a day, as is with great reaſon ſuppoſed they did of old.) Were thoſe arms that were once ſtretcht upon the Croſs, and ſtill are <hi>open</hi> to receive the true-penitent, were they but as <hi>open</hi> too, to receive the habitually diſobedient and impenitent, then would we frequent the Lord's Table.</p>
               <p>But does not the Wedding-Garment of Faith and Repentance and Charity, and Devotion and the like, does not this pleaſe us? Give me leave to ask, (as the Apoſtle did in another caſe) unto what then were ye Baptized? have ye <hi>put on Chriſt</hi> for this? And was it for this that we were early <hi>dedicated to him</hi> in Baptiſm, and <hi>received into the Covenant of Grace</hi> and Mercy; that when we with the Diſciples of old, ſhould have continued ſtedfaſtly to renew this Covenant in the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lord's Supper, and to <hi>ow<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n</hi> what was then <hi>done</hi> for us, when we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151744:19"/>could do nothing for our ſelves, and come and declare our <hi>willingneſs to ſtand to thoſe Engagements</hi> then made for us; to come and in perſon to ſhew our readineſs and our willingneſs to follow him in the ways of his Commands and holy Religion; that <hi>then</hi> we ſhould refuſe it? or if we do not refuſe it, yet come ſo ſeldom, <hi>as if we deſired to be excuſed from it.</hi> Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Oh whither will our Indevotion, our Lukewarmneſs, our Inconſideration carry us! Is this to act as they who now ſit at Peace and reſt in the Manſions of Glory, have done before us? And has not our Lord ſhed as much blood for us as for them? And are not our hopes and Promiſes and Expectations the ſame which they had? why then, <hi>Cur non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumus quod iſti &amp; iſtae?</hi> as the pious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid of old. Why cannot we (at leaſt in far better meaſures than now) do as they have done before us? whence is it then that our Practice is gone ſo far off from their frequency in this Heavenly action, their zeal and their fervour?</p>
               <p>Certainly, this muſt of neceſſity pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from a great and moſt deplorable <hi>want of Love to our Religion, or of Zeal for our Saviour, from a ſtupid unconcernment for a joyful Reſurrection:</hi> or (as was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151744:19"/>hinted) becauſe we find no <hi>taſt or reliſh in this heavenly food,</hi> this ſood of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, or from <hi>intolerable inconſideration.</hi> Hence, O hence is it in a great meaſure, that our <hi>Lives</hi> are ſo <hi>unholy,</hi> our <hi>Actions</hi> ſo <hi>uncharitable</hi> and unchriſtian, our <hi>thoughts</hi> ſo <hi>impure</hi> and <hi>prophane</hi> and <hi>incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate,</hi> and the <hi>whole frame</hi> of our Live ſo <hi>diſordered and diſcompoſed;</hi> and as this chiefly for want of a more frequent and devout uſe of theſe holy Myſteries.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Whence (ſayes one) came the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity and Holineſs of the firſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? Whence came their ſtrict obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Divine Commandments? whence was it that they perſevered in holy Actions with a comfortable hope and unweary diligence? from whence came their deſpiſing the World, their univerſal Charity? whence came theſe and many other Excellencies, but from a conſtant Devotion and frequent Communion? They who every day repreſented the Death of Chriſt, every day were ready to dye for Chriſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>We look upon that body to be ſickly, diſtempered and diſeaſed, and dangerous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ill, that allways loaths it's wholeſome food, and has no appetite to that which would be its only, or it's beſt nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151744:20"/>Thus, O thus! it is in the Caſe of the Soul; how <hi>ſickly and diſtempered,</hi> how <hi>diſeaſed</hi> and diſordered muſt that Soul needs be, that <hi>loaths</hi> it's moſt whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>food,</hi> the <hi>food</hi> of Angels? this <hi>nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment</hi> of the holy Sacrament; which if duely and devoutly taken, would ſo <hi>nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh it up</hi> to Salvation as to make it more <hi>healthful</hi> and holy, more <hi>chearful</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, more juſt and upright, more pure and devout and Angelical; 'Twould make it much more ready for the performance of any other Duty, more full of zeal and fervour, more conſtant and unwearied in all Religious actions. In ſhort, 'twould make it more ready for Death and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality.</p>
               <p>The holy Sacrament is call'd by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. <q>The Cup of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and ſurely if we do not thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Cup of Bleſſing, Bleſſing may be far from us:</q> Neither is it imaginable, That that man ſhould love Heaven and his Soul, or felicity or his Lord, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires not frequently to bath in that whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſtream, the blood of that immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Lamb of God that takes away the Sins of the World.</p>
               <p>Having thus ſeen what theſe texts of <hi>Scripture</hi> are that imply a frequency of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151744:20"/>Communicating, we ſhall briefly conſider the ſecond thing.</p>
               <p>Secondly, let us ſee what was the <hi>cuſtom</hi> and the <hi>practice</hi> of the firſt Worthies of the Chriſtian <hi>Church</hi> ſhortly after our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's time; and if in a few Inſtances we find them frequently meeting and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the death of their and our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lord and Maſter, Let us (remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring he has done and ſuffered as much for us as he had done for them) ever hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fit the Soul to take all opportunities we are able, to do in ſome degree as they have done before us.</p>
               <p>The firſt Inſtance I ſhall produce, ſhall be of a great and holy man,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>St.</hi> Cypr.</note> a Biſhop of the Church of Chriſt; who lived above two hundred and fifty years after our Saviour Chriſt; he tells us, that the Cuſtom of receiving it daily was obſerv'd in his days.</p>
               <p>Another who liv'd above three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years from our Saviour,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>St.</hi> Ambro.</note> ſays, Receive that every day, which may profit thee every day. And no leſs than a whole Council or Aſſembly of Devout men at <hi>Antioch,</hi> (the place where the Diſciples were firſt called Chriſtians, as we are told <hi>Act.</hi> 11.26. though not at the ſame time) decreed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151744:21"/>ſome ages ſince our Saviour's time, that thoſe ſhould be excommunicated, caſt out of the Church, who came to other holy offices and divine Services, but went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way without receiving the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>And, (to mention no more) a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father of the Church,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>St.</hi> Jerom.</note> who liv'd about four hundred years from Chriſt's time, ſaies the practice of daily receiving was continued to his time. Let us then with eyes ſhut and arms folded, when we are next alone and retir'd from the World, in a ſerious thought conſider, Did thoſe of old who owned the ſame crucifyed Jeſus with our ſelves, Did they as conſtantly do this in remembrance of him, as they did pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly meet to pray together or hear the Word? And is it come from once a day and once a week, to once a year, to once in our whole lives? Is it come to this? Is this all the ſenſe and apprehenſion we have of the neceſſity and advantages of this duty? Is this the obedience we ſhew to an <hi>Expreſs Command</hi> of our Saviour; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wholly to diſobey it, or perform as ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as poſſible we can? Is this the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation of the practice of the firſt ages of Chriſtianity? Is this all the reckoning
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151744:21"/>and accompt we make of that ineſtimable priviledge of <hi>being in Covenant with God?</hi> or of being called and invited to come and renew it again when we have broken our terms, and to have it ſigned and ſealed to us again? Was it for this, O bleſſed Jeſu! that thou haſt done and ſuffered ſo much for our ſakes? Was it for this that thou wert content for us to ſubmit to an <hi>Agony and bloody ſweat, to the Croſs and Paſſion, to a Death and Burial?</hi> And is it for this that we have ſo long owned thee for our Lord and our Redeemer, a tender and merciful Saviour? that ſome of us ſhould ſtupidly live in an habitual neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of doing this in remembrance of thee?</p>
               <p>And have we no greater ſenſe of, and concernment for the laſt words of a dying Saviour? ſhall the expiring breath of a dear Redeemer poured out for our eternal Intereſt, be loſt and in vain to any of us that call him ſo? O how much Reaſon have we to ſay of ſuch, Father forgive them, (or rather, father open their eyes) for they know not what they do.<note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor</hi>'s life of Chriſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But thus</hi> (as is obſerv'd by an excellent Prelate now with God) <hi>it hath fared with this Sacrament as with other Actions of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which have deſcended
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151744:22"/>from Flames, (the Flames of the Devotion of the firſt ages) to ſtill Fires, from Fires, to Sparks, from Sparks to Embers from Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to Smoke, from Smoke to Nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in the Name of God let me en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, are we willing to make <hi>any</hi> publick, thankfull, joyfull, acknowledgments <hi>at all</hi> of the love of our crucifyed Jeſus, and the great things he has done and undergone for the redemption of us and of our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren after us? if not, we are monſters of Ingratitude and Impiety. If we are at all willing ſo to do, why ſhall we not fit our ſoul to take all poſſible opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, while we are yet here below, and at this diſtance from him, to do this in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him?</p>
               <p>How can we think that our other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions ſhall be prevalent with, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to the Holy God without the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of our Saviour? and the merit of his ſufferings? and yet this is the way he hath appointed to give our prayers an Intereſt in his Sacrifice. Can we reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably ſuppoſe, that indeed any Duties whatever and the performance of them ſhall be accepted, when this great and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn act of Religious worſhip ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, omitted and neglected?</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151744:22"/>
               <p>O let us in our next retirements, when we are withdrawn from the noiſe and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult, and buſineſs and thoughts of the world, deeply think, ſhould we not have reaſon to be afraid, that <hi>no Petitions of ours, no Devotions, no works of Mercy, Piety, or Charity, no Faſtings or Alms, no hearings or readings,</hi> ſhall be accepted without this part of our Chriſtian Worſhip; Would it not further be a ſad and diſmal conſideration, to remember in the hour of Death or day of Judgment, that theſe and many other holy Actions ſhall fall to the ground, being vain and loſt, only for our <hi>wilful neglect</hi> of this holy Sacrament.</p>
               <p>Again in the ſame retirement from the World, and in your next meditations, conſider, what could you think of a rich and very wealthy perſon, that never in all his life ſhould be perſwaded to beſtow ſo much as the worth of a farthing to the poor and needy? Or, what thoughts ſhould we have of him, who never in the whole courſe of his life, ſhould offer up a prayer to God, either in publick or in ſecret? The ſame may we think of him that would never accept of an Invitation to fit and trim the Soul, to come, and with the reſt of his Chriſtian Brethren to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of theſe holy Myſteries: for they did
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151744:23"/>but diſobey a plain Command of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's; the one only diſobeyed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>feeding the hungry, and cloathing the naked,</hi> the other only refuſed obedience to the Command of <hi>praying without ceaſing;</hi> So the wilfull abſenter from the holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord, only diſſobeys the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Do this.</hi> Nay, I look upon this to be a greater piece of diſobedience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in this there is an obligation of love, Love infinite and unſpeakable, an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of thanks and gratitude to engage us. Do this in remembrance of me the Lord that bought you, the Lord that pay'd down the dear price of his blood &amp; Wounds, ſweat and groans, pains and death for you.</p>
               <p>Give me leave to ſay further, I ſhall never, I can never truly believe, you have any tolerable care of your ſouls, till I ſee this Holy Sacrament more frequented; till I ſee ſome evidence of your greater love to theſe holy Myſteries. Not how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, as if I would perſwade, or give encouragement by this, to wicked men while they continue ſuch, to approach this heavenly feaſt. But for thoſe who reſolve heartily by divine Grace to reform their lives, and (amidſt the diſadvantages of this life) are fully purpoſed, to Devote them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151744:23"/>in ſincerity, though not in perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to the Laws of our holy Religion; whatever elſe you do, yet I ſhall never, I can never ſuppoſe you have any tolerable Love or Zeal for our Dear Redeemer, while you habitually turn your back on his <hi>Holy Table.</hi> Nor can your conſtant attendance at the houſe of Prayer; your Zeal and Devotion there, your juſtice and integrity in dealing, your ſobriety and purity of life, be ſufficient to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me to think you have any truly conſiderable value for immortality, or that you make any tolerable proviſions for a happy Reſurrection, while you wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deny your ſelves the priviledge of feaſting on the Body and Blood of our common Lord, by which new life and Grace is conveyed to us.</p>
               <p>O how can I believe, you truly and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly repent of your Iniquities, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a pardon of your Sins, when you will not be at the pains to prepare your ſelves to come and beg it, and to have it ſeal'd to you? Or how can I think, that you deſire to be firmly united to Chriſt our head, or to be united to each other, when you refuſe to come and ſtrengthen the Union?</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:151744:24"/>
               <p>Surely, one might be apt to think we have loſt all ſenſe and remembrance of the Love of God in ſending his Son, and of the Son in coming to lay down his life for us, by this one intolerable neglect of ours. How can we go to God in our Prayers, and plead to him the meritorious Death and ſuffering of our Saviour, and yet refuſe <hi>to ſhew forth the Lord's Death till he come?</hi> and wholly ſlight, or very ſeldom attend on this higheſt Sacrifice of Praiſe and Thanksgiving? How long ſhall we call the Holy Jeſus <hi>Lord, and not do what he ſaith?</hi> How long ſhall we thus refuſe to keep the memorial of dying Love, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey a Command pronounc'd by his expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring breath?</p>
               <p>Little, O little do you conſider how great a reproach to Chriſtianity it ſelf, and how dangerous to your invaluable Souls, the conſtant omiſſion of this one excellent part of Chriſtian Worſhip is.</p>
               <p>Conſider, we do all believe, that Chriſt dyed for Sinners, and we have had the happineſs to have been baptized into this belief; we do profeſs to believe, that <hi>there is no other name under Heaven by which we muſt be ſaved.</hi> We all hope that his merits ſhall be applyed to us, that ſo we may for ever partake of theſe benefits pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151744:24"/>for us; and yet we are ſo impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, as that we will not have them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in ſuch ways, as he himſelf hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, in the performance of thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and the uſe of thoſe means which he himſelf has ordained to that end and purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>And (to uſe the words of a learned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) I ſee no reaſon why men may not as well hope to be ſaved without Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by Chriſt,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> of Religious Aſſemblies.</note> as well as without eating his fleſh, and drinking his blood in the Sacrament. For Holineſs will not ſave us without the merits of Chriſt, and I know not how we ſhould come by the merit of Chriſt, but only in ſuch ways of diſpenſing, conveying and applying them as he himſelf hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed; &amp; he has appointed no other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary way but this Myſterious Supper.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Having ſeen the Cuſtom and practice of the firſt Worthies of the Chriſtian Church in the pureſt ages; I ſhall upon the whole offer this further conſideration to common reaſon, Whether do we now ſuppoſe is moſt ſafe and Holy, to imitate as far as we are able, this pious practice of theirs of a very frequent communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, (remembring alſo, that thoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151744:25"/>Souls who lived ſo near the time of our Saviour, better knew his mind in ſuch caſes, than we, at this diſtance) or, very rarely to addreſs our ſelves to this Solemn Act of Chriſtian worſhip? In which are we more likely to pleaſe God and our Saviour, to do his will, and provide for a joyful Reſurrection?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Let us ſee and conſider a few Reaſons for the frequency of communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating.</p>
               <p>The firſt is this; That as our breaches of our part of the Covenant are too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent; ſo, ſeeing God is willing that yet we ſhould renew this Covenant again, and Seal it at the Lord's Table; how infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly willing ſhould we then be of ſo doing? The Covenant which we entred into with God in our Baptiſm, is this, <hi>Almi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghty God is pleas'd on his part to promiſe Pardon of Sin, Grace and Glory, if we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Conditions of Faith and Repentance, and ſincere, (though not perfect) Obedience.</hi> Here then let us fix our foot and conſider, how frequently, how miſerably, have we broken our part, of this Covenant of Grace! and is it not infinite mercy, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and compaſſion, that God is ſtill content and willing that we ſhould come and renew this gracious Covenant? Shall
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151744:25"/>not we be ready and deſirous to renew it for our own ſafety, our eternal ſecurity; ſhall not we be willing and earneſt ſo to do, when our God is willing; and when he calls and invites us to it? ſhall we not be ready and willing to renew it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, when the great God often calls and invites us to it? <hi>Oh how ſhall we eſcape, if we neglect ſo great Salvation!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>ſecond Reaſon</hi> for our frequent ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching this holy Table, is, <hi>That this is a Holy Duty which if duly and devoutly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, conveys great comforts, benefits, and bleſſings to us.</hi> Thus, Oh how would it confirm, ſtrengthen and encreaſe our <hi>Faith?</hi> how would it promote and height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en our Love to our <hi>Lord</hi> and Maſter Jeſus, and make it more flaming and ardent, more like the <hi>Zeal and Affection</hi> of the Cherubims and Seraphims?</p>
               <p>How would it promote and encourage <hi>Religion and a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver ſally Holy Life?</hi> How would it it promote <hi>our Peace, amd Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> and Love and <hi>mutual Endearments</hi> to each other, as we are travelling together over this Wilderneſs to the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> as we are paſſing along together over this World on in our journey to <hi>Jeſus and Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How would it ſtrengthen and confirm
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151744:26"/>our <hi>Hopes?</hi> How would it make our <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance</hi> more ſerious, more deep, and more effectual, Our <hi>holy Reſolutions</hi> more fixt and ſtedfaſt?</p>
               <p>How would it help us to <hi>ſubdue, and get the victory</hi> over our <hi>Iniquities,</hi> over our boſom darling Sin, whether it were <hi>the Sin of our Calling, or the Sin of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, or the Sin of our Conſtitution?</hi> How would it encourage us in all that is good, in all that's <hi>holy,</hi> in all that's <hi>juſt,</hi> and all that's <hi>upright,</hi> and bring us to a better <hi>knowledge</hi> of our own State and condition of Soul? How would it bring us to a near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and more intimate acquaintance with the Holy Jeſus, and with our ſelves alſo? What aids and aſſiſtances of the Grace and Spirit of God ſhould we receive with it? Theſe and many more than theſe are the bleſſings, and benefits, and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, which <hi>a frequent and devout</hi> commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating would convey to us. Say now, are not theſe great and ineſtimable bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings? Are not theſe deſirable? Are they not truly amiable and lovely? and to be earneſtly wiſhed for by all thoſe whoſe hopes and expectations are in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World and not in this?</p>
               <p>What, (my Beloved,) is it not an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuable bleſſing to have our Faith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed?
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151744:26"/>and yet by the due and conſtant participation of theſe Holy Myſteries, to how divine a pitch, and heighth, would it be raiſed? Is it nothing to have our hope confirmed? and yet by our fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent attendance on this holy Table, how full and lively, how raiſed and chearful would it be? how much a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ground and foundation ſhould we have for it?</p>
               <p>Is it nothing to have our Zeal, and Love to our crucified Lord, more inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and heightned? and yet oh how would the due frequentation of this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn act of Religious worſhip, exalt and raiſe and carry-up our Souls to him, and make them mount up upon the wings of Devotion, almoſt high enough to reach the pitch of Angels and freer Spirits? Is it nothing, to have our mutual Charity, and Unity, For bearance and Forgiveneſs of one another promoted, as we are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on together to the Grave and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality? why, nothing will ſo effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally do this, as the frequent meeting our Lord at this Heavenly Feaſt.</p>
               <p>Is it not a bleſs'd advantage and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to have our Reformation made more ſincere, effectual and perſevering? and yet in the devout and frequent uſe of thoſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151744:27"/>holy Myſteries, we ſhould find more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and arguments and encouragements for it than we could before imagine. We ſhould find, that in the ways of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Holyneſs and Virtue, we can do more by Divine aſſiſtance, than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we thought we could; and that in our moving towards the degrees of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, we can go farther than before we ſuppoſed we were able.</p>
               <p>Is it not a bleſſing to have a greater power and ability and ſtrength to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due a temptation, and to beat down and conquer a ſtubborn and rebellious Sin Is it not a bleſſing to come to a more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate and near acquaintance with our Souls, and how their accompts ſtand with reference to a joyful Reſurrection and happy Eternity?</p>
               <p>Is it not a bleſſing to come at laſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be delighted with, and encouraged it and taſt the ſweets and delicacies, the lightſomneſs and chearfulneſs of heart that accompany a truly Religious Life If theſe are bleſſings truely deſirable and amiable, why, never ſhall we come to have them ſo effectually conveyed to us as by our frequent and devout atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on this Chriſtian Sacrifice. And aſſure your ſelves, that upon your own
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151744:27"/>Experience, you will find it an undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble truth, that there is not one of theſe <hi>Benefits, Bleſſings and Advantages,</hi> but would (if we are not wanting to our ſelves) be diſpenſed to us. Well then, ſeeing our hopes and promiſes, are not ſo much here below, and we daily look when we ſhall be received to our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Society, and unknown Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, methinks theſe ſhould be irreſiſtable reaſons for a frequent and holy uſe of theſe Divine Myſteries.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Another reaſon is, that our frequent preſenting our ſelves at the Table of the Lord, would be a great Sign of our Love to Religion and Virtue.</hi> It would argue our <hi>love</hi> to <hi>Religion,</hi> as this is one great and ſolemn part of it, and as it is an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of many <hi>Christian Graces</hi> and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. It would argue our deep appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and conſideration of <hi>another World.</hi> 'Twould be an evidence of our <hi>deſires</hi> to make ſeaſonable a proviſion for <hi>Immortality,</hi> and of our endeavours to be ſuch as our Lord would have us. 'Twould be one great Argument that we deſired to be imployed and bear a part in <hi>Religious actions,</hi> with the reſt of our Chriſtian brethren, whenever we have opportunities, that we are earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151744:28"/>willing to bear a part with thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Souls here below, among whom we would <hi>ſtand</hi> in the day of Judgment. 'Twould evidence that <hi>our Faith</hi> is live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vital and obedient, that <hi>our Charity</hi> is truly Chriſtian, that Religion is our <hi>practice,</hi> not our <hi>profeſſion</hi> only. 'Twould argue, that we are willing to <hi>ſtand</hi> to the <hi>engagements</hi> of our <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> to our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt; that we reſolve manfully <hi>to Fight under the Banner</hi> of our Jeſus, againſt Sin, the World, and Devil, That we are will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſubmit our ſelves to the Goſpel, and to take on us Chriſt's eaſie yoak and light burden. Nay, a frequent and devout communicating would be a great Sign of <hi>our Devotion and frequency in,</hi> and love to all other Religious acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>And indeed how ſad and deplorable an evidence, does the wilful refuſer give of his prophaneneſs, his little love to Religion, and of his inconſideration? whereas I ſay, a due and frequent perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this holy duty, would argue the contrary; would be a good Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of our deſires to pleaſe God, and draw near to him; that we are wearied and laden with our iniquities, when we thus bring them to Jeſus to be caſt out,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151744:28"/>and when we come to take new Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt them.</p>
               <p>O may theſe conſiderations woo and win us over, perſwade invite and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage us to meet the holy Bridegroom of our Souls, who has appointed when and where to meet us! He has given the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation, he has made the appointment, and ſhall not we go forth to meet him? why ſhall we ſo imprudently any longer refuſe to give him thoſe demonſtrations of our Love to him and his Religion?</p>
               <p>Rather let us ſay, this day with one heart, and one voice, and one conſent, in the words of holy <hi>David, Pſ.</hi> 40.7.8. <hi>Lo I come to do thy will O God.</hi> I come O Jeſu to <hi>renew that Covenant with thee, which (and 'tis a ſad truth) I have ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably broken. I bleſs thee for the Call, and I come quickly to celebrate the memory of thy dying-Love. I come to own that I am a member (though unworthy) of thy Spouſe the Church, and come with the rest of my Brethren, to beg a portion and an Intereſt in thy meritorious death and ſufferings. I thank thee eternally for the Invitation, and I come with the reſt of that body of which thou art the head, to waſh in that Fountain that was opened for ſin and for uncleanneſs, and would not be found out of the number of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151744:29"/>thoſe holy Souls that are devoutly going to meet thee, for the whole World, in the day of Rewards and Puniſhments. Thou haſt done as much for me as for any one of them; with them therefore I thankfully come to do thy Will,</hi> to do this in remembrance of thee.</p>
               <p>O that thus we would be winn'd and woo'd to this holy action, by arguments of Love to Religion, by arguments of Zeal and Devotion, fervour, deſire, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and affection! and let us not be hall'd and dragg'd to it, only by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of Terrours and Horrours, Hell and Damnation.</p>
               <p>And may we yet grow and ſtill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in our Love to this holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo much and ſo long, till we come to deſire it, and wiſh and long for it! Which a great Prelate of our own,<note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi> Preface to holy Living.</note> and another pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſon make (to uſe their own words) one of <hi>their twelve ſigns</hi> of Grace,<note place="margin">Drexel.</note> and <hi>Predeſtination</hi> to Eternal life.</p>
               <p>May our love of it then ſo increaſe, till we come to be able to think it <hi>too long</hi> that our <hi>Lord tarries; too long</hi> till the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of Supping with him come about; <hi>too long</hi> before the time come
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151744:29"/>when we may meet him once more in his own Houſe at his own Table; and to be able, with a full and teeming heart, to ſay of his coming to us in that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly,</hi> thou haſt long tarried from that Soul that loves thee, from that Soul that <hi>thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt loves thee.</hi> St. <hi>Jo.</hi> 21.15.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the <hi>4th</hi> and laſt Reaſon that I ſhall mention is, <hi>that a frequent and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Communicating, would be an undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble argument of our flaming affection to and Love of Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How can it be reaſonably ſuppos'd we ſhould have any tolerable affection for that man from whoſe company we all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes deſired to be excuſed? from whom we run when he calls and invites us? up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom we turn our backs when he ſends to us to come and Sup with him? Can we truely call him our Familiar ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance or intimate friend, with whom we never care to be? This, O this is the Caſe between our Maſter Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus and ſome of us that call him ſo.</p>
               <p>But if we <hi>call him Maſter,</hi> for ſhame let us no more refuſe to apply our ſelves to this higheſt and chiefeſt piece of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; If we call him Lord, let us <hi>do what he ſayes,</hi> and he has ſaid, — <hi>do this.</hi> If
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151744:30"/>we call him Friend, (the Worlds beſt Friend) let us make haſt, and be glad to go forth to meet him. Let us be joyful, that he is willing once more before we dye, to come to us and to invite us to come to him. Let us not think it much to lay aſide our old <hi>ſpotted Garments</hi> when we are going to meet our Friend, the World's beſt Friend Jeſus. Let us not think it much to put on our <hi>beſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray,</hi> our Wedding-Garment when we are haſtening to go forth to meet our Friend, the World's beſt Friend Jeſus.</p>
               <p>If we call him the <hi>Captain of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> then let us go and Solemnly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and own our ſelves his Soldiers, and not ſhrink and ſtay behind, when the reſt of his great <hi>Army with Banners</hi> (<hi>Cant.</hi> 6.10.) is going ſo to do: but let us alſo go and declare our intentions and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions to follow him whitherſoever he ſhall pleaſe to call us, though it be to lay down our lives for him, (and yet in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, we ſhould do no more than he has done for us.) Let us go and publiſh our reſolutions to enter into no more leagues of Friend-ſhip with the <hi>Enemies</hi> of this our <hi>Captain,</hi> theſe enemies that once made him bleed, theſe enemies, (Sin I mean) that once made him ſweat drops
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151744:30"/>of blood, theſe enemies that flew our Captain. Let us in our very affections renounce ſuch Enemies, and go forth to meet our Captain, and humbly tell him, that we are purpoſed by his aſſiſtance and by his <hi>conduct</hi> thus to do. Let us tell him, that we are reſolv'd to <hi>renew the Combat,</hi> and reinforce our diligence with all our <hi>ſtrength,</hi> never more to deſert and leave him; and that we are now coming to enter into this <hi>engagement</hi> again, and ſolemnly to ſeal it: and that as we were once lifted under him by Baptiſm, when we knew it not, ſo now when we are come to know it, we are ready and will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſtand to it to the end of our days; and are thankful too, that he has <hi>brought us to the knowledge of this Grace, and Faith in him:</hi> and that he has given us this one one opportunity more of making ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn declaration of it at his own Table. Thus let us manifeſt our Love to our great Maſter Jeſus, our beſt Friend, the Captain of our Salvation Jeſus.</p>
               <p>But further, if we call him Friend, and this Friend of ours, be for a while gone off from us, ſhall we do nothing in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him? did he require us at parting (at leaſt not long before he left the World) to <hi>do ſomething in remembrance
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151744:31"/>of him,</hi> when he was gone, and had bid adieu to the World? Surely, if we knew not what it was, had it not been plainly revealed to us, how deſirous, how earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt would we be to know it, that ſo we might not fail to do it? we ſhould then (if we knew it not) be apt to ſay, <hi>what ſhould it be that thou wouldest have us to do, in remembrance of ſuch love as thine? O our Jeſu what ſhould it be? O that we could but come to the knowledge of it, that ſo we might inſtantly ſet about it.</hi> If ſo, conſider then, how far ſhould we be from refuſing to do it, when we certainly know what it is.</p>
               <p>What, is there ſomething to be done in remembrance <hi>of dying Love?</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in remembrance of a <hi>bleeding Friend?</hi> Something in remembrance of the <hi>great Lover of Mankind?</hi> Something in memory <hi>of a crucified Saviour, and a parting Redeemer?</hi> Surely one would think it muſt needs be ſome very hard and uneaſie duty, ſomething next to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, that there ſhould any be found in the Chriſtian World, refuſing to do this <hi>ſomething;</hi> and yet all this that we refuſe to do, is but to fit the Soul, and come and feaſt on his <hi>body and blood,</hi> in memory of his Croſs and Paſſion: and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151744:31"/>is this all the difficulty in that which we are to do? tremble then, at thy mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Ingratitude, and never more dare either come unprepared, or to keep a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
               <p>How ſhould this conſideration rather melt us into Love? Love (in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) ſuch as his, that is, dying Love? how ſhould it ſwallow up all our little and trifling objections, as the Ocean ſwallows up a drop of water? how ſhould ſuch conſiderations melt us into tears of Love, and then into thoſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and blow off all our fond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes and vain pretences againſt doing this, as eaſily as Feathers are blown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by a violent blaſt of wind? What can indeed reſiſt this, but a heart bent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on iniquity and prophaneſs and irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a heart never opened by any ſerious thoughts or apprehenſions of the <hi>Love of Jeſus?</hi> and how ſhould that conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on move us, readily and ſpeedily to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take our ſelves to the putting on of the Wedding-Garment of preparation, and infallibly take the very next opportunity of coming and ſhewing, that we are deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſible of this Love, and of our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer great neglects? and do it how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie ſoever ſome look upon the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151744:32"/>to ſit about them when 'tis on; do it, (that is) how much pain &amp; loſs; how much ſhame and reproach; how much diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage &amp; ſelf-denyal ſoever it coſts us in our endeavours to procure it; if the frequent uſe of thoſe holy Myſteries will be ſo great an argument of our Love to Jeſus.</p>
               <p>O let it no longer therefore be ſaid of any one of us that we ſhould live in the habitual neglect of this known neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary duty; and let it no longer be ſaid of us, that our Communicating was not as frequent as poſſible we could have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities for it. Let it no longer be ſaid of us, that we ſhould be ſo impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as not to be willing to renew our Baptiſmal Covenant, when our Lord is yet ſo willing to renew it with us. No longer let it be ſaid of us, that we ſhould be ſo inconſiderate as to live in the omiſſion and neglect of a duty, which if frequented would convey ſo many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits and advantages to us as we have mentioned. O let it no more be ſaid of us, that we ſhould ever hereafter live in the conſtant neglect of that ſolemn act of Chriſtian Worſhip, which if frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed, would be ſo evident a ſign of our great love to Religion and Piety, and of our deep apprehenſions of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151744:32"/>World, and our concernment for a joyful Immortality. Never, never let it be ſaid of us in the day of Judgment, that while we dwelt upon Earth, we were alway loath and backward, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to preſent our ſelves whenever we were invited to that holy and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and pleaſant duty, by the frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which, we might ſo plainly have ſhewn our greater love to Jeſus, by our readineſs to take all opportunities of commemorating his dying bleeding af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to us.</p>
               <p>And then, O let it never be ſaid of any of us, that the only reaſon why we ſhould or could be ſuppoſed to refuſe it, was, becauſe we would not be at the pains of <hi>putting on</hi> the Wedding-Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or endure the thoughts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of ſtripping our ſelves of the old ſpotted rayment of Sin and Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on! No, the old acquaintance muſt be parted with, the old <hi>Dalilahs</hi> divorced, the darling Iniquity that has long been near and dear to thee muſt be thrown off. But may it be henceforth never ſaid of us, that we had rather part from the <hi>ſweet Communion</hi> with the holy Jeſus, than renounce our <hi>fellowſhip with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful works of darkneſs.</hi> Why ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151744:33"/>of theſe things be ever ſaid of any one of us, in the hour of death or day of our Accompts? May they never be ſaid to us, or remembred in that day and hour, when it ſhall be impoſſible to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them!</p>
               <p>To conclude this head, O that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we would withdraw our ſelves from the World, and look beyond the Grave, and then look upon our ſelves as thoſe that are haſtning to Eternity; and then in that ſerious thought let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that e'r long, we ſhall find it to have been the beſt and moſt ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry imployment in the World, to have been frequent and devout Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants.</p>
               <p>O that ſometimes we would ſhut our Eyes, or take them off from the World, and then think how vaſt that Eternity is, that depends upon the holy manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this moment: and having ſo done, then tell me, how great the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity and advantages of this holy Duty do begin to appear.</p>
               <p>O that ſometimes we would look upon our ſelves only as Strangers and Pilgrims here, and that two or three ages hence, we ſhall all be forgotten, &amp; that then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall be remembred of us any more,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151744:33"/>but either our horrid unreformed Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or our ſincere holineſs, and Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of heart and life to the Goſpel of our Saviour: and then upon ſuch a cloſe and piercing thought as this, inſtantly conſider, how does this holy and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Duty appear to thee? and wouldſt thou not willingly have it then remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred of thee, that thou wert here below a devout frequenter of theſe holy Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries?</p>
               <p>O that Sometimes we could ſeriouſly fix our eyes in a holy Meditation on that glorious day, in which our Lord ſhall come to place his faithful Servants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all further doubts or fears, poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of ſin or temptations, infelicities or Scruples of Conſcience: Tell me in ſuch a thought as this, would it not be a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed conſideration to be in a State, in which we could be truely able to <hi>love his appearing?</hi> (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.) why, never ſhall it be thus with us, 'till we come to be devout and frequent attenders on theſe holy Myſteries. Nay, I will appeal to thine own Soul in the Caſe, when wert thou ever able ſo heartily and true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to love the thoughts of thy Lord's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, as when thou wert but juſt come from his holy Table? Couldſt thou not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151744:34"/>have been willing then, that all thy buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in this World might have been o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and that he might have then come, and taken thee into the air with him, and ſet thee down in the Manſions of eternal Holyneſs? and why then ſhould not thy frequency in this holy action be ſuch, as that he may almoſt even at any time <hi>come,</hi> and not fail to <hi>find thee ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O that ſometime we would look upon this life, as a ſtate and condition in which we are plac't by the eternal God, to fit and trim the Soul, for the ſociety of thoſe holy Worthies that are gon up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us; and then in that thought conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how far ſhort our practice comes of their daily and weekly communicating: Or, that laſtly, we would ſometime look back too, and conſider again, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all our former days that are ſlid away from us, thoſe only ſhall ſhortly be remembred with joy, in which we have done ſomething in order to a joyful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and a ſafe Eternity. Say now, would we not in ſuch a thought as this, wiſh heartily, that we had a better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt in the Regiſters of Heaven than we yet have? more eſpecially that we had many more devout performances of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151744:34"/>this holy and heavenly duty recorded there than we have? and if we find Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thus to think of our paſt dayes, Oh why ſhould we henceforward have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to think the ſame of our future days then, when they alſo ſhall be over, and we ſhall be brought to the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of the Grave?</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore in the name and words of our dear and holy mother the Church, earneſtly beſeech you no longer to continue ſo much ſtrangers to, ſo wilful neglecters of this holy Duty: (— <hi>and if any man neglect to hear the Church, let him be unto thee as a heathen man and a Publican.</hi> St. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17.) and ſhe invites us thus, — <q>I bid you in the name of God, I call you in Chriſt's behalf, I exhort you as you love your own Salvation, that you all be partakers of this holy Communion. And as the Son of God did vouchſafe to yield up his Soul by death upon the Croſs for your Salvation, ſo it is your duty to receive the Communion in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the Sacrifice of his death, as he himſelf hath commanded: Which if ye ſhall neglect to do, conſider with your ſelves how great injury you do unto God, and how ſore puniſhment
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151744:35"/>hangeth over your heads for the ſame, when ye wilfully abſtain from the Lord's Table, and ſeperate from your brethren who come to feed on the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet of that moſt heavenly food.</q> And thus much of the firſt general head, to ſhew, that this is a neceſſary holy and Chriſtian Duty to be frequently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and the neglect of it infinitely dangerous.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:151744:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> This do in remembrance of me.</head>
               <p>SEcondly, we come now to ſee to what end it was inſtituted or appointed by our bleſſed Saviour.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it was inſtituted and ordained for a perpetual and devout remembrance of him our Redeemer, ſo ſays our Lord himſelf, St. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19. <hi>This do in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of me.</hi> —</p>
               <p>As if he had ſaid, in remembrance of mine Agony and bloody ſweat for your intereſt; in remembrance of my bitter ſufferings and my death; in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of my Laws and Doctrines; in remembrance of my Reſurrection and Aſcenſion; in remembrance of my Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory for you, over Sin and Death and Hell; in a comfortable remembrance of this too, that upon your Repentance, Reformation, and Sincere obedience for the future, your paſt iniquities ſhall all be placed upon the accompt of the Croſs,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151744:36"/>and be covered with the Robes of my Righteouſneſs; and that I will ever be your Jeſus, your Saviour; Do this, do it for a continual and grateful memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of theſe things: that ſo ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance as this of me your dying Lord, may fill your Souls with Love and Devotion, your Wills with holy reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; that ſo it may excite and ſtir up holineſs and virtue in your lives, and may unite and endear you to your Lord and Saviour, unite and reconcile you to each other, and promote peace and love, and unanimity and Charity among you, who are all members of my body, of that body (the Church) of which I am the head: that ſo meeting together fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently at this feaſt of Charity, when you remember my love to you all, this may promote love among you all, and may increaſe Faith and Piety and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in you, and incourage you in it, till at laſt you come <hi>to meet me in my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> Thus was it firſt inſtituted for a thankful remembrance of our Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and all he has done and ſuffered for us.</p>
               <p>Was it ſo? and Lord can it ever be, when this was the great intent and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of it, that any that name thy ſacred
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151744:36"/>Name, ſhould be unwilling to come and bear a part in ſuch a remembrance? Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks that Soul that ſhould refuſe to do ſo, refuſe to fit and trim it ſelf, to go forth and remember the Lords of Life and Glory, with the reſt of his Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an brethren, ſhould upon ſuch a thought, be ſorrowful and greatly troubled, that almoſt all others ſhould go to claim and beg an intereſt in the death and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of their Lord, and he alone be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concern'd in it; he alone ſtay back, and refuſe to put his hand to the Petition, and his Seal to the Covenant. Methinks again, ſuch a Soul ſhould conſider and ſay, how imprudent, how inconſiderate is my caſe and condition, how dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous is my ſtate of Life, that while others are reſolving and preparing to go, and hoping to feaſt acceptably with Jeſus, I ſhould be alone backwards? Here I am, wallowing in Sin, living in a heedleſs, ſtupid, careleſs ſtate of life, following my luſts and vices, and take no care to get out of them, no care for my Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, making no proviſion for Eternity and a joyful Reſurrection; but always ſuffer my ſelf to be hurried away by Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, born down by every ſlight Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and am kept off from fitting my
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151744:37"/>ſelf for the Table of my Lord, by vain pretences, and little Excuſes, by every Sin that looks fair and offers a little de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light or advantage; and ſhall I live and dye thus? Shall I continue in this State till all opportunities be over and at an end with me? Why, O why ſhould not I, even I alſo labour to put on the Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Garment, <hi>and ſee if he will yet be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated,</hi> and reconciled to me, <hi>and bleſs me, even me alſo?</hi> Rouze then O my Soul, awake and ariſe ſpeedily from the death of Sin, to the life of Righteouſneſs; off with thy old poluted Garments, (by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace) forever, on with thy better rayment of Faith and Repentance, Piety and Charity; and come my Soul, let us go ſpeedily to remember the love of our dying Lord; for moſt others, they are either gone, or going; Come my ſoul, at laſt let us go willingly and chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, others they are haſtening, <hi>and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks the Love of Chriſt begins to conſtrain us to,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. Come then let us haſten to commemorate and meet him, with the beſt preparations we can make; for others they are ſitting trimming and adorning the Soul ſo to do: and the ſame Lord is ready with his aſſiſting Grace for me, even for me alſo, if I am
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151744:37"/>not wanting to my ſelf, that is, earneſtly beg, and faithfully uſe and imploy it.</p>
               <p>Well then; my Chriſtian Brethren, all of them they are going, and ſhall I be the only perſon that ſhall ſtay behind? they are now reſolving to celebrate the memory of a bleeding Redeemer, and ſhall not I alſo? Oh how will my Lord take this at the day of Judgment? how ill will he take it at my hands, that I alone ſhould ſtay behind, lurking with his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Sin and Satan, when others throw them off and bid adieu to them, to go to meet and remember Jeſus?</p>
               <p>May each Soul that is ſeeking for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and has any temptations to abſent himſelf, thus argue, and thus conſider; and let him ſay further, would I be will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſtand among thoſe who have fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently and devoutly remembred the Lord of Life and Peace, <hi>the Author and Finiſher of our Faith?</hi> (<hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2.) Is not this my deſire? is it not my earneſt hope? Come my Soul, ſay once more, come, let us ſtand with them now, let us ſtand with them now and ever here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, while we ſtay with them here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, let us be found among them now imploy'd in this heavenly action, among whom we would willingly be found at
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151744:38"/>our Lord's Second coming to judge the World. Let us not (my Soul) prefer the pleaſures of Sin for a Seaſon, let us not chooſe the trifling profits and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of Sin for a ſeaſon, but when others go forth to meet the Lord, and commemorate the death and paſſion of their bleſt Redeemer, may it never be my lot to be abſent, much leſs may it never be my choice to be ſo; and when others ſhall be proſtrate before him, and by this heavenly action joyntly renewing their Covenant with him, recounting what he has done and ſuffered for them, Sending up the Incenſe of praiſes and thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings, joyntly Suing out their pardon from the Court of Heaven, with one Soul and heart, ſending up holy petitions to him, to be by him preſented and handed un to the Father; thus making a joynt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for a ſafe and holy Eternity; far be it, O far be it (I ſay) from me, to refuſe to bear a part with them: but with all the devout Souls of the Chriſtian Church, be ever hereafter ready and joyful, and forward and glad of all opportunities to be imployed in the ſolemn, devout, and holy and thankful remembrance <hi>of the Lord that bought me; And</hi> That's the firſt end to which this Sacrament. was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:151744:38"/>
               <p>Secondly, it is alſo a Seal of that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which God was pleaſed to make with us by Chriſt, which we entred into at our Baptiſm; that gracious Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant made between God and us, by the Mediator Jeſus. Thus 'tis called, <hi>the blood of the New Testament,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> St. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.28. [<hi>or of the new Covenant.</hi> Now this new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, between God and us, made by our Saviour, is (as was before ſaid) that God will give pardon of our Sins, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Grace, and everlaſting Glory, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Conditions of Faith, Repentance, and ſincere Obedience. Our Lord in thoſe Myſteries, Seals this to us, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us, as he is the God of Truth, and cannot lye or deceive us, that he will perform his part; We on the other hand, ſeal back this to him, that we will ſincerely and heartily endeavour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our part: We are then to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that thus it was promiſed for us in our Baptiſm, when we knew nothing of it; but here we come in our own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to take thoſe advantageous Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on our ſelves, to renew them by our own hand, our own act and our own choice.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:151744:39"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is my Blood of the new Covenant,</hi> ſays our Saviour; to this our Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites us, to ſhew firſt his death till he come, and next, to renew our Covenant with him; to Seal it again, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare our reſolutions, to labour more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually and diligently for the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of our dayes to ſtand to our engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and diſcharge our Conditions of it.</p>
               <p>O my Lord, (ſay now upon this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration) who am I, that thou ſhouldeſt leave thy Fathers boſom, to be the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate <hi>Mediator of a new Covenant</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and me? but oh who am I, that after ſo many breaches of it, thou ſhouldſt call and invite me, once more to come, and renew it with thee again? who am I, that thou ſhouldſt ſpeak to me, to come and enter again into a further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of it? what a tender mercy is this? how bleſt a priviledge is this? that thou art pleaſed to call me once more, to come and receive my Pardon, if but yet for the future, I do in an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſincerity perform my part of the Covenant? What long-ſuffering is this, that thou ſhouldſt ſtill bid me to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, and have my Pardon ſealed too; if my terms be but yet performed? and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151744:39"/>how far have I been from deſerving any thing of this at thy hands?</p>
               <p>And O my Jeſu, ſhall I refuſe to come, and humbly accept of thoſe mercies which thou art yet pleaſed to offer me? and though I have broken <hi>my part</hi> of that Covenant which this Sacrament is a ſeal of, ſhall I not thankfully come and accept of thy deſires to make good <hi>thine,</hi> if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all this I am not yet wanting to my ſelf?</p>
               <p>Shall I not rejoyce in an opportunity of confirming and ratifying in my own perſon, that which was done for me without my knowledge in my Baptiſm? ſhall I not come and declare my deſires to be found now and ever within the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace? Or ſhall I voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly withdraw my ſelf from it, and not come and put my hand and ſeal to it, with others of my Chriſtian Brethren? ſhall I by my refuſal to renew it, declare for Sin, for the World, Fleſh and Devil? Far be it from me, (ſay) O my dear Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, far be ſuch thoughts as thoſe, No, I come willingly and readily and chearfully, with a Soul, and Heart, and Mouth, full of Praiſes and Adorations, to renew this gracious Covenant, to own my ſelf thy Diſciple, thy Servant, thy
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151744:40"/>follower; I come to ſee thy dying bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Love, and to imprint it afreſh upon my memory: I come to ſee thy earneſt deſires of accompliſhing my Redemption repreſented to me; I come to behold thy Agony and bloody ſweat, thy Croſs and Paſſion; thy Body broken, thy Blood poured out for me: I come freely and openly to own my unworthyneſs to come at all, to own how undeſervingly I have walked of thoſe benefits. I come to ſue a Pardon for my breaches of my terms of the new Covenant; I come to ſeal it again with thee, and humbly, and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully adore thee for this mercy, that thou calleſt me once more to do ſo.</p>
               <p>O that inſtead of ever entertaining a thought of abſenting our ſelves, we would imploy it in ſome ſuch meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as theſe,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> Relig. Aſſemb.</note> or with the words following of that excellent perſon before mentioned? <q>That frequent Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions are as neceſſary to our ſpiritual growth and increaſe in holyneſs, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the decays of our Graces, and to renew our ſtrength and vigour in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, and to procure the pardon of Sin after a relapſe, and to call back the holy Spirit when he is withdrawn
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151744:40"/>from us, as bread is to keep our bodies, in conſtant repair; and did men love their Souls as they do their bodies they would no more neglect the Supper of our Lord, than their daily food. And if we have been guilty of any breach of Covenant with God, by ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing on the commiſſion of any Sin, when we have with tears bewailed our Sin and renewed our Repentance, here we muſt renew our Covenant, and by approaching the Table of our Lord, declare, that though we are Sinners, yet we are not Apoſtates, (that is, we are not fallen from the Faith or the Chriſtian Religion) but that we ſtill own our Covenant; and by the Grace of God, which we now implore and hope to receive, reſolve to continue ſtedfaſt in it while we live.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:151744:41"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of Examination of our Selves.</head>
               <p>I Come next in the third place, to ſhew briefly, how we are to come prepared to this holy Sacrament.</p>
               <p>The chief parts of preparation are theſe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt, Examination of our ſelves.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, To enter then into a holy Courſe of Life, by Repentance and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions of a future ſincere Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, To bring with us a lively faith in God's mercy through Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>Fourthly, To bring with us Charity to our Brethren.</item>
                  <item>Fifthly, To bring with us Devotion and a pious frame of Soul.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Of each of theſe briefly.</p>
               <p>Firſt, of Examination of our ſelves; to this St. <hi>Paul</hi> adviſeth, — <hi>Let a man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat of that bread, and drink of that Cup.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:151744:41"/>
               <p>And here we are to examine (as far as our memory can inform us) what our breaches have been of that Covenant which we entred into with God and our Saviour in Baptiſm. We told you, that our part of the Covenant is, Faith, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and ſincere Obedience. But alas! we have moſt miſerably gon aſtray, and have often, knowingly, wittingly and willingly broken all theſe parts of that holy Covenant.</p>
               <p>As to our <hi>Faith</hi> firſt, how dull, lifeleſs, and unactive has that been? how little have we ſhewed it by our works? by works of Mercy, Piety, Charity, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion? How little have we ſhewed our Faith, by our Conformity of heart and life, to thoſe Goſpel duties to God, to others, and our ſelves, by which we ſhould have ſhewn it? St. <hi>Ja.</hi> 4.18.</p>
               <p>Again as to <hi>Repentance,</hi> how unſincere has that been? how have we return'd ſoon after our beginnings of it, to our old iniquities, <hi>like the Dog to his vomit, or the Sow that was waſhed to her wallowing in the mire?</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22. Can we not eaſily remember the time, when we had wept over our Crimes, and thought our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance had been deep and hearty, that we inſtantly fell into them again, upon
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151744:42"/>the next temptation that look't fair? and forgot our holy Reſolutions. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as a Reformation or change of life, is the life of Repentance, and without that, (at leaſt in the Goſpel meaſures, that is, in the moſt hearty ſincerity, though not entire perfection) what we call Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, is <hi>but the bowing down the head like a Bull-ruſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then as to that other part of our Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>Obedience,</hi> how unſincere has this been too? how partial have we been in it, performing one duty, and omitting two; reforming one iniquity, and then ſoon after, entring upon another inſtead of it? Thus, can we not remember, that we may have changed the Luſts of our Youth, into the Covetouſneſs of old age? the intemperance and vanity of our younger days, into revenge and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, in our growing years? and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a univerſal reformation, often exchanging only one ſin for another? Then again, how groſs has our Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance been of our neceſſary and indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable duties? and yet of thoſe that we have known, how few have we faithfully diſcharged? how has the World Fleſh and Devil ſtept in between us and our former reſolutions of Obedience? So diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151744:42"/>have we broken our part of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
               <p>But now does our God and Saviour call us to renew it once more? and will he be reconciled to us yet, if we heartily return and renounce iniquity, and give up our ſelves to obey his commands? and is he ready to give us an aſſurance of this, and to confirm it in the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
               <p>Come my Soul, let us examine our ſelves, and conſider what our breaches have been of this gracious Covenant, at leaſt our greater and our more notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, heynous breaches; that is, what our omiſſions of our Duties have been; what our known commiſſions have been, that ſo we may come to a true <hi>and deep Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation</hi> of our ſelves before God; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ſenſible</hi> of our Crimes, <hi>and heavy La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> we may come to Jeſus to be <hi>eaſed</hi> of them; and that ſo, ſeeing them, we may loath them; that loathing them, we may remember this when we come to the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Lord: and that we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it too, when we are come off from that holy Table, and are going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad into the World again, and throw them off forever.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:151744:43"/>
               <p>That ſo we may ever remember how dear they coſt us, (and if returned to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, are like to coſt us dearer) how dear they coſt our Jeſus, and yet how willing he is to be reconcil'd. And when the Temptation returns again, we may beat it off (by divine aid) with ſome of theſe conſiderations, ſome of theſe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances, and eſpecially this. That for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs belongs not to him, who ſins and repents, repents and ſins on ſtill; but to him who repents ſo, as to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his Crimes and his Iniquities.</p>
               <p>Plainly and in ſhort, the meaning of Examination, is to conſider theſe three things following.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> To examine whether you right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtand that Vow and Covenant which you made with God in your Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and which you come to renew and Seal again with God in the Sacrament: If you do not, 'tis (I ſay it again) briefly this; Almighty God on his part, graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly promiſes a free pardon of all your paſt-Sins, Grace here, and Salvation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after by Jeſus Chriſt; Upon Condition, that we diſcharge our part; that is, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly believe the truth of the Goſpel of our Saviour, Truly Repent of all our Sins, and by ſincere reſolutions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151744:43"/>endeavours of future Obedience, give up our ſelves to follow him in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs and Righteouſneſs all the dayes of our Lives.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> To look into the Soul, and as far as our memory will reach, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what our Iniquities, (eſpecially our greater iniquities) have been, with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to God, Our ſelves, Or our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, that we can diſcover we have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured upon, either in Thought, Word, or Action.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To enquire, what Omiſſions of Duties (eſpecially what greater omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions) either to God, our ſelves, or Neighbours, we can charge upon our ſelves, either of Thought, Word, or Action.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And when we have ſo done, to bewail them heartily, (as well as our Secret-Sins, with David <hi>Pſ.</hi> 19.12.) to take new <hi>Reſolutions</hi> againſt them, to go <hi>and declare</hi> thoſe our holy reſolutions at the <hi>Holy Sacrament,</hi> and when that is over, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>watchfully and ſincerely to keep</hi> thoſe pious Reſolutions. This is (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhort) the meaning of Examination; as to the particular heads of Examination, and helps to it,<note place="margin">Whole Duty of Man.</note> I refer you to the book mentioned in the Preface.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:151744:44"/>
               <p>But then let us Examine not only what our iniquities have been, but alſo how great they have been; how they have been aggravated or increaſed in their guilt, or made greater by ſeveral wayes and means. For thus, Examine, have not ſome of them been againſt <hi>much light, much knowledge?</hi> have we not ruſht into them foreſeeing them plainly, and done it wittingly and willingly? Examine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, has it not been a Sin or Sins not only of knowledge, but of which we might <hi>eaſily conſider before-hand</hi> the great guilt and dangers? Nay poſſibly did weigh and conſider it, and yet after ſuch conſideration have reſolved to chooſe it, for ſome vain delight or trifling advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage it brought with it.</p>
               <p>Examine further, was it not a Sin which when we adventured on, <hi>our own Conſcience flew in our face,</hi> and ſtept in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and it; and yet we broke through all Reſiſtances and oppoſitions of Conſcience?</p>
               <p>Examine again, had not thy Sin this guilt to make it greater, that it has <hi>fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently</hi> been committed? ſo frequently, that no vows, no former purpoſes, of amendment or obedience, could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain thee from it, but didſt wilfully
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151744:44"/>break all theſe, to come to thy crime?</p>
               <p>Examine further, it is not grown up to a greater height? has it not this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of its guilt, that 't'as been ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently adventured upon, as that it is grown into <hi>a cuſtome, a ſecond Nature with thee,</hi> ſtrongly grafted and deeply rooted in thee?</p>
               <p>Examine again, is it not ſo deeply rooted in thee, that thy <hi>Conſcience is even hardened and ſeared</hi> againſt it? that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions ſent from God to reclaim thee, have not wrought upon thee? or it may be 'tis of ſo Long continuance, that the charitable and private admonitions of thy Friends and the Ambaſſadours of God, have been in vain with thee; ſo deeply rooted, that notwithſtanding theſe, the long cuſtom of the Sin, has endeared thee to it, ſo as to like it in thy ſelf and others too.</p>
               <p>Having inquired therefore, what thy iniquities are, examine whether they have not ſome of theſe <hi>aggravations</hi> that make them greater and more heynous. If thou findeſt it ſo upon enquiry, Oh let the conſideration of it, work thee into a <hi>deep ſenſe</hi> of, <hi>and humiliation</hi> for it, and that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation for it, lead thee to <hi>ſincere Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition,</hi> to grief of heart, that thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151744:45"/>thus have requited the infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of a tender Father, of a dear Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; and that the good and <hi>holy Spirit</hi> ſhould have been ſo <hi>grieved</hi> by thee. (<hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30.) And let the end of all this be, that thou now at laſt, come to a <hi>hatred and abhorrence</hi> of it, and that thou art now going to Jeſus, to take up new Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of Reformation.</p>
               <p>Such as this let thy Examination be, look back thus upon thy paſt dayes, look into the State of thy Soul, ſearch it nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly, and as ſtrictly as thou canſt, and ſee if there be any one <hi>known wilful Sin</hi> lodging in it; and beg of God to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it to thee, and then take this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of throwing it off forever. Or, if after a long Cuſtom and habit, it be not to be thrown off all at once, then (at leaſt) begin thy faithful reſolutions, and war againſt it now; never leaving, till by the grace of God (always ready for thoſe that beg and faithfully uſe it) thou haſt obtained the Victory, and ſubdued it: and here at the Lord's Table, thou wilt get greater ſtrength againſt it, new Arguments againſt it: The remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thy dying Saviour's bleeding Love, will aſſiſt thee in the conqueſt of it.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:151744:45"/>
               <p>Come then, let us go to our Jeſus, and to the Entertainment which he will make for us, and let this <hi>Examination</hi> bring us to a <hi>ſenſe</hi> of our Sins, that the ſenſe of them may bring us to a <hi>Humiliation;</hi> and that humiliation may bring us to <hi>ſincere Contrition;</hi> and that Contrition may bring us to <hi>Repentance, Reformation and Holyneſs;</hi> that ſo we may come at length to ſee the Pleaſures and Advantages of a Religious and Holy Life, and taſt thoſe Sweets and Delicacies, which we yet little think there are in ſuch a ſtate of Life; and that ſo our paſt impieties may all be covered with the Robes of our Lord's Righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>But that you may never hereafter be at a loſs in your Examination, ſo as to neglect this Holy and Heavenly Duty, becauſe of endleſs doubts and fears, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you are qualified or no, do but try your ſelves by theſe following queſtions. As I was baptized into the Religion of the ever bleſſed Jeſus, ſo am I willing to ſtand to theſe engagements, (to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of my power) that were then made in my name? Do I ſeriouſly believe the Goſpel to be the Truth of God? and will I labour uprightly to conform my heart and life to it? Do I repent of all
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151744:46"/>my Sins, (known and ſecret) and my former diſobedience? Have I a lively and ſtedfaſt Faith in Chriſt my Saviour? Am I ſenſible of my unworthyneſs to come to this Table, and deſirous to be made more worthy? that is, am I ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of my Crimes and Iniquities, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of Pardon, and of Grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form? And do I reſolve and purpoſe a ſincere reformation of any thing that I can diſcover in my ſelf at any time, which is contrary to the Will of God? — Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, do I reſolve and purpoſe, to ſet my ſelf with watchfulneſs and diligence againſt that boſom Sin whatever it be, to which I know my ſelf moſt inclin'd? Do I harbour in my heart no one known wilful Sin at this inſtant? Do I deſire, and heartily endeavour to underſtand the Goſpel of my Saviour, and to direct my Life and Actions, according to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines there delivered? And wherein I ſhall at any time hereafter fall, through frailty, infirmity, or unawares; do I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, ſpeedily to riſe again by Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and by a greater Care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and watchfulneſs for the future? Am I in Love and Charity with all men, and willing and ready to do any good action for Friends and Enemies? and do
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151744:46"/>I wiſh and deſire their good, of Soul, and Body, Goods and good Name? — Am I deſirous to renew this Covenant of mine with God, and to come and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully commemorate my Dear Saviour's bleeding, dying Love for me in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament? To come there to receive freſh tokens of his Love to me, and to beg and receive more of his Grace, to help me to perform theſe things, and to live a ſincerely Holy and a Chriſtian life?</p>
               <p>If from a ſincere and honeſt heart, you can anſwer Yes to theſe particulars, then lay aſide your doubts, away with your fears and ſcruples; And in the name of God come, and come with joy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, with a thankful, lightſom and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful heart, to this moſt holy, and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and pleaſant duty in the World.</p>
               <p>And thus much of Examination.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Second part of Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, That upon ſuch Examination, we then enter into a holy Courſe of life, by reſolutions <hi>of a future new obedience.</hi> Let this be the end and intent of Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of our ſelves, that ſo having found what our frequent, too frequent breaches of our Covenant, of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151744:47"/>of our Saviour have been, we may ſeaſonably, while our day laſts, take up hearty and unfeigned purpoſes of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging them uprightly, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of our days. Thus holy David, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.59. <hi>I thought on,</hi> [or I examined] <hi>my wayes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Accuratum exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men inſtitui. <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and turned my Feet unto thy Teſtimonies.</hi> Let our Examination of our ways, have the ſame end, the ſame fruit and effect that his had. Here let us come then, and renew and declare our <hi>Chriſtian Reſolutions,</hi> when our Lord calls, and invites us, and is willing to have us do it.</p>
               <p>More eſpecially here do thou go to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and renew them againſt that <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Iniquity,</hi> to which (upon thy Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination) thou foundeſt thy ſelf moſt frequently tempted: bring with thee an enrire hatred of all, but eſpecially of <hi>that,</hi> which hath ofteneſt foyl'd thee hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and got the Victory over thee, and may be moſt like to return upon thee, and do ſo again. And as now thou art to come in an hatred of it, ſo think and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider by what <hi>wayes and means, Companies and Temptations</hi> it may be moſt like to ſteal in upon thee again. Conſider by
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151744:47"/>what <hi>occaſions,</hi> in what <hi>buſineſs</hi> or <hi>imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> 'tis, that it may be like to entice thee again, and bear thee down before it; and that ſo often, ſo long, till it may be thou dye in it, and thou lye down in the grave with it, and the holy Jeſus come and find it unmortified, and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unreformed; and thou be at his ſecond coming Sentenced for it, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Lot and portion of the damned.</p>
               <p>Having in theſe thy holy reſolutions conſidered the occaſions of it, or by what <hi>delights</hi> or <hi>profits</hi> and <hi>advantages</hi> it uſually tempts thee, and prevails over thee, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour then, (how dear ſoever it coſt thee) to get out of the ſnare and the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; reſolve, whatever mortifications, ſelf-denials or diſadvantages in thy Worldly affairs it ſtand thee, to get out of the way of it. In the firſt place, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour now then, to foreſee what the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of it may be, by which wayes the temptation enters upon thee; by what Companies, (I ſay) buſineſs, Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; for the Love of what pleaſures, advantages and intereſts thou art led to it; that ſo foreſeeing them, thou mayeſt <hi>abſtain from all appearance of evil.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.22.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:151744:48"/>
               <p>Reſolve hence-forward, to ſtep out of the way of theſe occaſions, whatever ſhame or reproach it may coſt thee from man; that ſo thou mayeſt follow Jeſus uprightly and chearfully, and ever here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, be a ready, willing, joyful and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Communicant. And when thou haſt found out the occaſions of it, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they were, Conſider, and ſay, And is this that petty Intereſt, or that vain delight, that comes to rob me of my Soul? my Heaven, and my Immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? And is this all that it can ever give or promiſe me in exchange of them? Is this all I ſhall get by my Complyance with them whenever they come again? And ſhall I do ſo any more? ſhall I em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace their motions any more? No, on my Soul, on, and as thou art going; look back no more, faint no more, give out no more; thou knoweſt the utmoſt of thoſe Pleaſures or Profits, they can bring thee in, but thou knoweſt little, or not half of thoſe vaſt felicities and joyes that await thee in the place of Glory; On therefore my Soul, and be content to ſtay for thy Delights and advantages, till but after the death of one Life, (and that's no longer than thou wouldſt be content to ſtay for the Reverſion of a
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151744:48"/>large Eſtate) and then ſit down in the full Enjoyment of them to all ages, and thou ſhalt be at reſt forever, at peace forever, happy and holy and ſafe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. And thus, let us enter upon a holy courſe of life, <hi>by reſolutions of a future ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere obedience, and by actually putting off all known Sin whatſoever.</hi> And that's the ſecond thing as to Preparation.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, let us bring with us a <hi>lively Faith, in God's mercy through Chriſt.</hi> That is, ſtedfaſtly believing, that for his ſake, our offended Father will be reconciled to us, if with Repentance and ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions of a ſincere obedience to his Commands, and a future Reformation, we give up our ſelves to him.</p>
               <p>And not doubting of this, let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and ſay; who am I, that after ſo many acts of wilful diſobedience, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny habitual Impieties, ſo many known neglects of my holy Duties, there ſhould, upon my ſincere Reformation and new Life, be any arms yet open to receive me? What, are there any poſſibilities for me of being yet accepted upon my hearty returning? Can theſe arms that were once ſtretcht out upon the Croſs, and nail'd to it, be ſpread ſtill to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace me, upon my becoming a new
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151744:49"/>Creature? me, who have as it were trampled upon the blood of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant? Are there hopeful poſſibilities yet left, of my receiving infinite benefit by that blood, if I am willing to have the merits of it applyed to me, and fit my ſelf to have them ſo applyed? And may I yet be accepted to eternal ages, if I go in the name of Jeſus, with a faithful pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent Converſion to my offended Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Why then, with the Prodigal, <hi>I will ariſe and go to my Father;</hi> and if he ſhould have Compaſſion upon me, ſhould I not rejoyce that ever I went to him, and bid adieu to my impious Courſes? I will then ariſe and go to him, <hi>and ſay, Father, I have Sinned.</hi> And if I reſolve thus to go to him, I have one to go with me, and intercede for me too; One that can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and ſhew to my Father the price of my Redemption: One, who (if I thus penitently go) will ſtand between me and my Father's Wrath, between me and the ſorrows of Eternity. One, that can ſhew Blood and Wounds to plead for me to my offended Father. One, who, if we are truely deſirous to waſh our Sins in penitential tears and yet cannot, can repreſent to my Father, that he wept blood for me; and 'tis one, in whom
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151744:49"/>our Father is well pleaſed: One, that can prevail, and do any thing with this our Father. And becauſe we cannot hope that he will be reconciled to us, but by the merits and mediation of this our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, let us go to him firſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech him to intercede for us.</p>
               <p>But where ſhall we go to find and meet him? why, at his holy Table he will not fail to meet us, if we go thither faithfully, penitently, charitably, and devoutly; there 'tis he often calls and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites us to meet him, and expects and ſtays for us there; ready (if we come thus qualify'd) to go with us to him.</p>
               <p>O my Soul (ſay) Come let us go to this our Jeſus then, Let us go and Sup with him, and humbly tell him how the Caſe ſtands with us, how diſobedient we have been; and how heartily earneſt we are to return and be accepted. And having his Son our friend and Advocate, Let us not fear to ſay to him, with an awful humility. <hi>Father I have ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Heaven, and before thee;</hi> But oh my Father, look upon thy Son, and my Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
               <p>I can only confeſs, and ſorrow, and ſue for pardon, but he has atton'd for me too, Let his wounds plead for me.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151744:50"/>See (O my Father) that ſide the ſpear pierc't for me, and there <hi>made way for me to his very Heart.</hi> Look on thoſe Sacred hands that were nailed to the Wood; See there how the pointed Iron drew for me in his hand the line of Life, the line of Life Eternal. Let his bleeding palms be an Expiation for mine, that have been ſo often <hi>lifted up to ſmite my brother,</hi> ſo ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom raiſed in my Devotions. Let thoſe Feet, the nail alſo bored, be an Expiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for mine, that have been ſwift to ſhed blood; or ſlow <hi>to run the way of thy Commandments.</hi> Thus O Father, tho I have ſinned, he has ſuffered, and atton'd; though I have <hi>ſinned againſt Heaven,</hi> he is there to plead and mediate for me; his merits are infinitely more than my Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties.</p>
               <p>And when thou haſt thus in the Name of Jeſus, humbly ſought the favour of thy offended Father, would it not be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of infinite Joy to think the Redeemer of the World ſhould intercede for thee, and ſay Behold O my Father, a penitent, a true and contrite penitent, one that with the Prodigal had eſtrayed from thee, but he is returning, and he ſorrows not only for fear of Hell and puniſhment, but he grieves for having offended a
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151744:50"/>tender and compaſſionate Father. The conſideration of his very ingratitude melts him into tears, and his Contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alſo has wrought in him ſincere reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of amendment of life. Behold O my Father, to ſuch contrite penitents are my merits to be applyed, to ſuch haſt thou promiſed mercy; Let all his paſt Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities therefore be charged upon my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt.</p>
               <p>Say now, would not this be a bleſſed conſideration, to have the Saviour of the World thus pleading and prevailing for thee with thy offended Father?</p>
               <p>Why then go to him, but ſo qualified as we have mentioned, and he will be heard in thy behalf; for thy Father is gracious and merciful, ſlow to anger, and of great kindneſs. <hi>Joel.</hi> 2.13. And that's the third part of a Preparation.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, We are to bring with us univerſal Love and Charity to our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. To come with a readineſs and willingneſs to be reconciled to them who have injured us; and if we have done the wrong, to be ready, and actually to endeavour, to reconcile them to us; according to that of St. <hi>Matth.</hi> chap. 5. v. 23.24. <hi>If thou bringeſt thy gift to the Altar, and there remembrest that thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151744:51"/>hath ought againſt thee; Leave there thy gift before the Altar, and go thy way, firſt be reconciled to thy Brother, and then come and offer thy gift.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to inſiſt on this the more briefly, clearly and diſtinctly, we are to conſider, that the Charity we are to bring with us, conſiſts, firſt in Forgiving, ſecond in Giving.</p>
               <p>Now as to the firſt of theſe, the two great and uſual Miſcarriages in our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, are firſt <hi>our Loathneſs</hi> and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs to <hi>forgive.</hi> Secondly our great <hi>unwillingneſs</hi> when we have done a known injury, <hi>to go and ſeek a reconciliation,</hi> and to deſire to be at peace with him that we have injur'd.</p>
               <p>We are loath in the firſt place <hi>to forgive;</hi> It may be we have liſtened to a Tale-bearer, and we have been told an idle ſtory, and ſuch a one has ſpoken ill of us, or railed on us; Inſtantly we ſwell, and are all in a flame, and can think of nothing but revenge and malice, and a perpetual hatred, and it may be nothing but his blood will ſatisfie our revengeful humour; and bitterly ſay preſently, <hi>We will be even with him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:151744:51"/>
               <p>But is this the patience, and meekneſs, and ſelf-denial of the Goſpel? Is this the forbearing, <hi>forgiving one another, if any man have a quarrel againſt any one, as Chriſt forgave us? Col.</hi> 3.13. Is this to love Enemies, and to bleſs them that curſe us? <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.34. Is this our beſt imitation of the Example of our great Maſter Jeſus? But let us not always ſo learn Chriſt, but endeavour to bring the Soul to that mortified, calm, and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful temper, as to be ready to forgive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, and to bear them meekly, ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and temperately; and when the <hi>Tale-bearer</hi> ſhall come to thee, and tell thee, that ſuch a one has reproacht thee; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, poſſibly it may not be true,<note place="margin">Si probra nobis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè oleant, &amp; verbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Impacta malis na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> rideant, ut vix modeſto difflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes gaudio Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus alto gratias altas Deo, <hi>Ac Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probanti</hi> lene pacis oſculum, Haec ſolida tandem eſt hilaritas frater Leo, Inambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantum Regia in Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis via, Angel, Gaz.</note> and then thou art angry with him without a cauſe. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider again, it may be it was in a very great Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and by this time he may be ſorry for it. However labour to bring the Soul to that Chriſtian pitch and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition as to be able to ſay. <hi>Has he ſpoken this of me? God forgive him for it;</hi> or to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151744:52"/>ſay to the bearer <hi>Remember me to him, and tell him I heartily forgive him, and ſhall be ready to do him any office of Chriſtian Love, whatever he ſayes of me.</hi> This would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the Tale-Bearer, and <hi>heap Coals of fire on the head of</hi> the injurious Perſon, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.20. Coals of fire, not to burn or inflame him, but to melt him into Love, or into ſorrow for the injury. This would be an excellent imitation of that great Lord of ours, who prayed for his perſecutors, and laid down his life for his Enemies.</p>
               <p>At leaſt Conſider this, who would loſe the benefits and advantages, the joy and the Comfort, and Satisfaction of being a Holy Communicant, only for the ſmall and unchriſtian pleaſure of a revengeful Word, a revengeful look, or a revenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful action? Or conſider how much eaſier is it to forgive an injurious, ſpiteful word or action, than to lye under the wrath of God to eternal Ages?</p>
               <p>Alway too, let us take this for an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Rule, that if we Copy out the Example of Chriſt, in forgiving, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the reproach be, God will force <hi>Light</hi> out of <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> bring <hi>Glory</hi> out of that which was intended for our <hi>Shame;</hi> and clear up our Innocence, if in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151744:52"/>an humble holy and patient Life, we be content to truſt him with it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The ſecond miſcarriage in this part of Charity is, our great <hi>unwill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingneſs,</hi> when we have done a known in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, to go to the perſon, <hi>and ſeek and deſire a reconciliation</hi> with him. This I confeſs is a thing ſo much a ſtranger to the World, that few look on it as a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: But when our dear Redeemer has commanded it, why cannot we deny our ſelves ſo far as to be content (I ſay for a known injury) to go to him, and offer to be reconciled? Oh no! the World will call us fools, and whatever becomes of it, our proud necks will never ſubmit to this part of the Chriſtian yoke: But conſider, we renounced the World in our Baptiſm, and ſhall we then ſuffer it to rob us of our Innocence and Duty? Let the World account it ſo, Remember, our Lord ſees not as the World ſees, nor judges as the World judges. Again, if we be ill ſpoken of for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Duty, that is,<note place="margin">St. Matth. 5.11.12.</note> for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs ſake, great then is our reward in Heaven. And let us be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſtay for it, till we ſhall receive it there. Again, let us not liſten to the voice of an irreligious World in matters
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:151744:53"/>of Religion; but above all, let us conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, our Lord has gone in the high way of the Croſs before us, he endured it, and deſpiſed the ſhame. O let us more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily do ſo too, in this caſe, Looking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Jeſus. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.1.2. Let us remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber too, That Chriſt is come to mortifie our carnal tempers, and to teach us ſelf-denyal, and to bear the Croſs; and what an excellent inſtance, would this readyneſs to go and deſire; and offer to be reconciled to thoſe whom we have knowingly injured, be of our deſires to imitate our Saviour? and if we were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil'd and laught at, to ſay with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr of old, <hi>Nunc incipio eſſe Chriſtianus.</hi> Now I begin to be a Chriſtian, and to be likened to my Saviour. To conclude this point, how much eaſier is it to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be reconciled, to acknowledge our fault, and ask a forgiveneſs when we know we have injured, than to bear the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of Eternity? and 'tis a deplorable conſideration to think, that we can deny our ſelves nothing, bear nothing, do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, though a little againſt the grain, againſt fleſh and blood, for the ſake of Immortality, for the pleaſures of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament, and the Love of Jeſus.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:151744:53"/>
               <p>Secondly, The ſecond part of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſiſts in <hi>Giving.</hi> Alms and Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have in all ages of the Church, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied the feaſt of Charity; and with great reaſon is it, that in this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn act of Chriſtian worſhip, we ſhould humbly offer ſome part of our poſſeſſions to God, as a token of this, that we thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully own, we hold all we have from him, and therefore deſire to pay back ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing again to him; that is, to thoſe whom he has made his Receivers: and the uſual miſcarriages in this caſe, are two likewiſe, either firſt, we come to this feaſt of Charity, <hi>without ſetting apart any thing</hi> for the needs of our poor brethren, or elſe ſecondly we bring <hi>too little.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the firſt of theſe, Conſider, when we relieve any at our doors, that's (often) becauſe of their importunity with us, or it may be to be rid of them; when we relieve by a Rate, that's by conſtraint, and the Laws compel us: But this is a free-Will-offering. Never let us fail therefore, when we come to ſee freſh tokens of our Saviour's Love to us, <hi>who for our ſakes became poor.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.9. then, to ſet apart ſome evidence of our Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to thoſe who bear his Image, and whom he has made his proxies, and that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151744:54"/>our Lord takes it as done to himſelf; and that for an Alms, we may receive a bleſſing. Never therefore in this Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly action, let us appear before the Lord empty.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly the other fault is, that our alms are often too <hi>thin and ſlender.</hi> 'Tis true indeed the holy Scripture has not ſet down the exact meaſure or rule of giving; but therefore, even for that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reaſon, we ſhould do well to give even beyond our ability, rather than fall ſhort of it, that being the courſe that is moſt ſafe and moſt holy, conſidering, <hi>that he that ſoweth ſparingly, ſhall reap ſparingly, and he which ſoweth bountifully, ſhall reap bountifully.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6. and ever remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that 'tis the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation ſomewhere of a pious Prelate,<note place="margin">Biſhop of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Conner.</hi>
                  </note> (now, through Chriſt, reaping ſome of the fruits of his unknown Charity and Piety) That the buſineſs of the great day of Judgment ſhall be tranſacted, and the Sentence chiefly paſs, according to the meaſure of our works of Mercy and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as he infers from St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.31. to the end.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:151744:54"/>
               <p>'Twere eaſie to produce admirable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the vaſt Charity of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of old, ſuch as to this age might ſeem almoſt incredible, for as a learned Perſon obſerves of them,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Cave</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſt.</note> 
                  <q>They looked upon the Poor as the Treaſure and ornament of the Church, by whom as by bills of Exchange, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned their Eſtates into the other World.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Let me therefore offer you this one Conſideration, to be ſeriouſly laid to heart, in your next ſober and retired thoughts, would we be but content to cut off from our <hi>vain Expences, needleſs viſits,</hi> our <hi>Exceſs and extravagancy,</hi> our <hi>vanity or folly,</hi> or what we may lay out on, either <hi>Lust</hi> or <hi>Intemperance,</hi> or in <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting our brother, in a revengeful malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and contentious Law</hi>-Suit, or <hi>the like;</hi> we might have a good portion for the Poor, and opportunity for many more charitable actions, than are yet recorded above; and might have a large <hi>Treaſure laid up in Heaven,</hi> at the end of or Sixty or Seventy Years, yet never the worſe in our Eſtates, at the end of the year, or the end of our dayes; beſides the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of a bleſſing here and hereafter,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151744:55"/>from the Eternal God, who has paſt his word to us. And why then can we not ſecretly lay out that on our Kingdom, on our Eternal Inheritance in Reverſion, which would elſe be expended on our jol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and exceſs, in vain and uſeleſs Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences?</p>
               <p>Further, he that has injured his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by fraud or deceit, or any other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, is in Conſcience abſolutely bound to reſtore, or make reſtitution to him again; but in caſe he be deceaſed, we are then to make it to his Heirs or Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors. But poſſibly it may ſo happen, that we may have been unjuſt to ſome, or in ſuch wayes, that we cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly know who they are; In this Caſe, the Reſtitution is to be made to the Poor. Now conſider, what an excellent oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity we have of ſo doing, by our Alms at this holy Sacrament; alway remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, that the Reſtitution be rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the injuſtice done, than in the leaſt degree to come ſhort of it. And that's the fourth part of Preparation.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, we are then to bring with us a great Devotion, and pious frame of Soul.</p>
               <p>Let us be very careful to lay aſide all thoughts and conſiderations of this lower
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151744:55"/>World, and all things elſe that may clog and hinder the Soul from being then wrought up to a <hi>Sprightly, Holy, Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Devotional temper;</hi> and earneſtly beg of God by prayer to aſſiſt us in our cloathing our ſelves in the Wedding Garment, that ſo we may go to meet our Saviour acceptably and chearfully, as we would to meet the deareſt Friend on Earth, whom we had not ſeen in many years before.</p>
               <p>And having with us a deep <hi>ſenſe and ſight of our Iniquities,</hi> begot in us by <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination,</hi> and a <hi>lively Faith</hi> in the infinite mercies of our God, through our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, having our <hi>Charity truely Christian,</hi> and our <hi>Devotion high and Angelical,</hi> let us with joy and pleaſure go to Jeſus, and declare our <hi>reſolutions</hi> to be his unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and faithful Servants and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; utterly abhorring all known Sin, and ſincerely reſolving for all known duty.</p>
               <p>And let us ſay of our old Iniquities, Be content to lay down your Necks, quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſubmit to be thrown off, for I am going to renew my Covenant with my dear Redeemer. Be content, ye my old Debaucheries, Prophaneſſes, Luſts and Intemperance, Oaths and Blaſphemies,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:151744:56"/>Malice and Injuſtice, and the reſt of you, to part from me, who am reſolv'd to take my leave of you, and to go and be more cloſely united to the Holy Jeſus, and to go on in my journey to the new Jeruſalem; adieu to you all, and though we weep at parting, 'tis not becauſe I muſt leave you, but becauſe I have been too long with you, and had not done ſo ſooner.</p>
               <p>And now my Soul, (may the devout perſon ſay) ſeeing we have done with them, let us raiſe and exalt one affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for our Lord is coming; and he is coming (if yet we are not wanting to our ſelves) to bring us a pardon ſealed with him from God, and to re-eſtabliſh our title to a glorious Inheritance: and we ſhall ſhortly bleſs the day, that ever we were perſwaded thus to do.</p>
               <p>Stay, methinks we begin to feel ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the pleaſures of Religion alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſomething of ſatisfaction in our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry firſt reſolutions of holyneſs; Oh what will it then be, when we are better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with our bleſſed Saviour, and his holy and Heavenly Doctrine! what will it be when we come to his Table, and have long frequented it, and given up our ſelves, intirely to him, as we now
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151744:56"/>hope to do? Come then let us begin it now.</p>
               <p>And oh my Soul, could we but for a while ſteal out of the body, that we might be the more free and lively, and active and unwearied, in our thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings, praiſes and Hoſanna's to that Lord whom we are going to meet.</p>
               <p>But however, Let us now ſay, <hi>I believe, Lord help my unbelief,</hi> for I come to have my Faith ſtrengthned: I am grieved and wearied with the burthen of my Sins, but I come from them to thy arms, the Sanctuary of reſt and peace, where wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Souls alone can lay their Heads, and bring their Cares and Sorrows, to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of them, and to have them turn'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Peace and Pleaſure. Thou (Lord) art he whom my Soul loves, and ſuffer me to ſay with thy Servant St. <hi>Peter,</hi> — Lord <hi>thou knoweſt that I love thee.</hi> And whatever thou pleaſe to deny me here, deny me not thy Grace and Aid, to cloath me in that Wedding-Garment which thou will pleaſe to accept.</p>
               <p>And may the pious Soul further ſay, Away away from me, all my leſſer Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of this life, that are apt to draw aſide my thoughts from Holyneſs; Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me not now, when I am about to ſup
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151744:57"/>with Jeſus: and come and welcom to me all holy thoughts, holy deſires, and holy Reſolutions; for you my heart is open at the welcom news of going to feaſt my Soul with the Body and Bloud of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the World.</p>
               <p>And be entreated Lord, to come and fill my heart, and take up thy dwelling there, and turn out thence every thought, and deſire, and inclination whatever it be, which thou art not willing ſhould dwell with thee. Be entreated Lord, to poſſeſs thy ſelf wholly of it; for I am coming to offer it up and preſent it to thee. And I am loath, when thou ſhalt come to take poſſeſſion, that thou ſhouldſt find any thing there, but holy deſires, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine breathings, earneſt longings after thee, pantings after Immortality, holy hopes, and devout affections. Fill it O my Jeſu, fill it up with thoſe for me, who am coming to meet thy glorions Majeſty, by the neareſt approaches I can make to thee on Earth; that So I may never miſs of thee at thy Table, or ever go away without a bleſſing; and when I ſhall go forth into the neceſſary concerns of this preſent life again, ever let me keep ſuch a flame alive in me, that ſo the old Enemies may no more be lodged
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151744:57"/>there, or the old temptations prevail with me; but that alwayes hereafter, when they ſhall come and ſeek to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained again in my heart or affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I may have this anſwer ready for them, <hi>Away from me, Jeſus has taken poſſeſſion there already; Trouble me no more, the room is full, and the door is faſt ſhut, to keep him there, and you from thence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With theſe, or ſome ſuch meditations as theſe, let us raiſe our Devotions then, and ſtir up our affections, which in this, are like other Flames, the more they are moved and ſtirred, they appear the more bright and ſhining.</p>
               <p>Or let the pious heart, again ſay, Oh my Saviour, thou haſt touched me with ſecret but ſtrong inclinations, to be with thee at thy Table, and to take hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward, all opportunities of ſo doing; O make them greater than yet they are, and may they never ceaſe to be growing, till I come to meet thee in thy Kingdom. O that thou wouldeſt but look upon this heart of mine that pants after thee, as a heart fit to be wrought upon by thee, to be made to do ſo, infinitely more than it does! That it may never more be contented to take fewer opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to commemorate the Death and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:151744:58"/>love of a crucified Lord, than all that it can poſſibly have: and when the day of my communicating is over, that I may mourn, and ſigh and long for the return of it again. O let the time come, when my Soul ſhall be wrought up to this pitch and temper never to be ſo well at eaſe, or ſo full of joy as when it has lately come from, or is ſhortly to go to a holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. 'Tis true, O my Redeemer, and 'tis a ſad trueth, I have long carried a World of unholy deſires and ſenſual inclinations about with me, and they have long followed me, and made my love to this Sacrament but dull and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; But I now hope they are all going off from me, to make way for that and thee. I have long fancied, I might have found happineſs in ſome things of this World, but I now begin to be perſwaded and to find, it is only to be found with thee and thy Religion.</p>
               <p>I can eaſily remember, when I have been greatly troubled at ſmall diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this lower World, but never at my diſappointing my ſelf of this holy and Heavenly feaſt, and can likewiſe as eaſily call to mind when I have longed for, and been pleas'd in vanity and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, much more than for a holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151744:58"/>but 'tis ſome comfort to me, that at laſt I can feel the thoughts of it to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to appear pleaſing and joyous, and that thoſe old Clouds of Darkneſs begin to be ſcattered: and let thoſe flames of love to thee, never go out again, never more return to coldneſs and aſhes; and may I ever be much more afraid leſt they ſhould do ſo, than at all the troubles, and all the diſappointments, and all the reproaches of this World: May I but live and dye with thoſe, and then let all other things be as thou pleaſeſt.</p>
               <p>And now O my Redeemer, come and take poſſeſſion of my heart while 'tis thus warm with the Love and deſires of thee, while by it's pantings and divine breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings 'tis moving towards thee, and ſtands open for thee. May my eager purſuits of either <hi>Riches, Honours,</hi> or <hi>Pleaſures</hi> of this life, never more ſhut thee out thence, but be thou pleas'd to reſt there, <hi>'till I ſhall be caught up in the Clouds to meet thee in the Air.</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4.17. <hi>and be ever with thee.</hi> As this of all things is now my earneſt deſire, ſo may it ever be, 'till that glorious day: and then all my doubts and fears ſhall be over and at an end, all my temptations and inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to Sin, and my frailties and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151744:59"/>ſhall be cured; all my ſcruples of Conſcience, my tremblings, and my fears to diſpleaſe thee ſhall be ended, and be to me as if they had never been at all. But before that time come, ſuffer me O my Lord, to ſigh out my deſires to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways with thee, as near as I am able to be, on Earth, at this diſtance from thee.</p>
               <p>And O my Soul, ſhall we begin then to take this Heavenly courſe now at the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament? We will, by Divine aid. On then, our Lord invites us, and calls, <hi>Come unto me, all ye that are weary and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi> St. <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.28. And ſeeing all things are ready, and he expects us, let us ſay to him, <hi>we come to do thy will,</hi> we are weary and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy laden, we come to find reſt and eaſe, we come Lord Jeſu, we come quickly. With theſe, or ſome ſuch meditation, let us then ſcrue up the Soul to a devout frame and temper. And thus much of Preparation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:151744:59"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Conſiderations after Receiving.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> what is fit to be conſidered and done after Receiving.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>FIrſt, thankfully meditate on the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercy and long-ſuffering of God, that he has been pleaſed to give thee this one opportunity more, of renewing and ſealing again the Covenant of Grace, who haſt ſo often broken thy Conditions of it.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, labour to imprint a deep re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of any promiſes or holy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions there made, between God and thy Soul, and be watchful in the keeping of them.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, earneſtly beg of God, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt thee in the keeping them, and in the walking for the future in the wayes of Religion and Holyneſs.</item>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:151744:60"/>
                  <item>Fourthly, meditate on the danger and the guilt thou runneſt into, if thou la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour not more ſincerely afterward to keep thoſe thy pious purpoſes, and thy felicity if thou do.</item>
                  <item>Fifthly and Laſtly, by looking back on this divine and heavenly, and pleaſant duty, think and meditate, how lovely and chearful and pleaſurable, a Religious life muſt needs be.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>thankfully meditate on the infinite mercy and long ſuffering of God, that he has been pleaſed to give thee this one opportunity more of renewing and ſealing again the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, who haſt ſo often broken thy Conditions of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this Conſideration, who is there but muſt needs ſay with David, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 34.8. <hi>O taſt and ſee that the Lord is good.</hi> We that have lately taſted, and have ſeen how good the Lord is, how gracious, to have given us one opportunity more of renewing our Covenant with him; ſhall we, can we forbear to publiſh it? Can we ever ceaſe to be thankful? No ſurely, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let us be ready to encourage others ever hereafter, to go from whence we have come, and taſt and ſee how good the Lord is.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:151744:60"/>
               <p>However, let each particular Soul, be deeply ſenſible, and conſiderate of this goodneſs of the Lord which he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted; O my Soul, (ſay) has our Jeſus admitted us once more to his Table, and permitted us to ſeal our Covenant again, to renew our reſolutions and purpoſes of obedience? and would he do it after ſo many old breaches of it? and is he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling yet to be reconciled, upon our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and future ſincerity in Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? and has he confirmed this to us in the Sacrament? O infinite Mercy and Compaſſion of our God! Well, my Soul, let us never forget it, but ſay with Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 103.1.2. <hi>Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul, and all that is within me, bleſs his holy Name: Bleſs the Lord O my Soul, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not all his benefits.</hi> Let us conſider a little, might not God have ſnatcht away, and have called us preſently before him, in the midſt of ſuch or ſuch a crying Sin, which we can eaſily remember, and not have given us one call more, one oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity more of a reconciliation? he might very juſtly. Might he not have call'd us to our particular judgment in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, in the very act of ſuch or ſuch an Impiety, of this or that Luſt or Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance injuſtice or perjury, Oath or
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151744:61"/>Execration, Debauchery or uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? Might he not have done ſo, <hi>after our long and wilful neglects of this holy Duty,</hi> before ever we approacht to it? and how might it have been now with us, had he taken that advantage againſt us? Might he not have hurried us away, to eternal unknown woes, without giving us theſe advantages, which we now by his Grace may improve to the purpoſes of a bleſt Eternity? And ſhall we not, my Soul, ſhall we not improve them, to the uſes of Immortality, when our Lord is thus willing we ſhould? Let us do ſo then, and do it heartily, chearfully and conſtantly; and let this goodneſs of the Lord lead us to Repentance and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and invite us to holyneſs and Religion, that's the firſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>after receiving, labour to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print a deep remembrance of thy Promiſes or holy reſolutions then made (or before) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and thy Soul, and be diligent in keeping of them.</hi> O let not the old Love, the former affection to Iniquity, return any more; but if the temptation do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, ſtay and remember, how odious, how deformed and ugly the Sin appeared then to thee, when thou wert at the Lord's Table, and then it was, that it
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151744:61"/>appeared moſt truely as it is: and then next, let this engage thee to recal thy pious purpoſes there; for alas! theſe are not to abide with thee only for an hour or a day or a week, but to the end of our dayes: and how hypocritically ſhould we deal with our God, ſhould we inſtantly forget that we have renewed our Covenant, and our purpoſes of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience with him, upon the Alarum of a Sin that promiſes much, and ſhows fair.</p>
               <p>However, Conſider before-hand, the temptation will come again, whatever thy reſolutions now are, (and do thou expect no other) and 'tis likely thou wilt not always be in this temper of Soul that thou now art in. The opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for thy Sin will be fair again; but doſt not thou now reſolve againſt it? I ſuppoſe thou doſt: But alas! this thou haſt done heretofore, (perhaps often al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo) and promiſed univerſal obedience to this Saviour; and yet haſt fallen again, as ſurely as a man falls that is ſtruck with a Thunderbolt; and thus it may be thou haſt gone round all the dayes of thy Life, Sin'd and repented, received the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Supper, and yet ſtill fallen as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently and as ſurely as ever, and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:151744:62"/>remain'd in a State of Sin and Death.</p>
               <p>Thus I ſay, it may be, thou haſt run on in this Courſe many years, and dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled thy guilt with thy dayes, and always upon the next occaſion and opportunity, forgotten that ever thou didſt repent and reſolve amendment of life. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, this is a very ill ſign (yet) of thy Condition, and it is extreamly dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. Much (perhaps) above half thy days have gon round in this Circle; And now if thou wouldeſt, thou haſt not half of them left to dedicate to Religion, and the ſervice of the holy Jeſus, and to the bleſſed Severities of Piety and virtue. And what's now to be done then? O at laſt (now) be more ſtrictly watchful and diligent, in keeping thy Reſolutions againſt it; and againſt all occaſions of it alſo, whatever <hi>ſelf denial,</hi> or ſhame <hi>or reproach or difficulty</hi> it coſt thee: Get at leaſt ſom tolerable ground againſt it now, never leaving, till thou haſt crucified and ſubdued all known habituall wilful ſin whatever, and laid it dead at thy feet.</p>
               <p>Remember too, that now is thy time, that now thou haſt yet fair advantages; but if thou imploy them not to the uſes of Eternity, and in order to the conqueſt
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151744:62"/>and victory over thy darling Sin that has ſo often born thee down before it, thy Lord may e're long, bid thee lay aſide all thy buſineſs here, and come and appear before him, and find it uncrucified, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reformed, and unmortified in thee.</p>
               <p>Conſider further, if ſo, why when thou art laid on the borders of the Grave, and coming to the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Death, thou wilt then with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row perceive and find, that by that hour all thy pains about it would have been over, and all thy trouble at an end; and would have been as if they had never been; and nothing left to do, but to ſit down in eternal peace; all thy combats would then have been ended, all thy mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications over, every difficulty of thy journey paſt through, and thou wouldeſt have had nothing more to come, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (through thy Lord's merits) to ſit down and to enjoy the fruit of thy dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and thy Victory, in Reſt and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and joy and ſafety.</p>
               <p>Come then in view of theſe hopes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider once more, that after all that thou haſt done, the old temptation will return upon thee, and what art thou reſolv'd to do if it ſhould? wouldſt thou without any reſiſtance of it <hi>ſubmit,</hi> and <hi>tamely
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:151744:63"/>yield</hi> to it again? Doſt thou not reſolve with ſincerity of endeavours to get ſome ground of it, if not the victory? art thou fully purpoſed to oppoſe and reſiſt it? If not, to what end haſt thou begun thy holy Courſe of life, if thou intend only to go on in it ſo long till thou find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt a fair opportunity to do otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>If this be thy Caſe, if thou wilt run thy race no longer than thou canſt do it with eaſe, or no longer than thy Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Intereſts or deſires, or the Devil are quiet, and forbear to tempt thee; thou art then as ſurely gone as ever.</p>
               <p>Conſider therefore, now while they are at reſt, before they come to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate and earneſt with thee again, (for they certainly will) how thou mayſt beſt reſiſt them, or be out of the way and moſt ſecure from them, from all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, all occaſions of them, out of their reach and violence. Whatever your Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity be, try whether there be not an abſolute neceſſity before it be ſubdued, and thy reſolutions kept, to mortifie thy great deſires of the <hi>Riches, Honours,</hi> and <hi>Pleaſures</hi> of the World. Do but try for a while, how ſafe thou wouldſt be then, how much further from all danger of a relaps: and be ſure of this alſo, that
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151744:63"/>whenever it returns, it will (like other Enemies) fall upon thee there, where thou art weakeſt and leaſt fortified.</p>
               <p>Whatever therefore thy ſinful inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be, O double thy guards there, that the Enemies of thy Soul and of thy cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified Lord, may never more find thee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed and unprovided, at their next re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn upon thee.</p>
               <p>Further, if thou hopeſt to keep thy holy Reſolutions againſt all known Sin, then beware, leſt thy affections to it, ſhould not be left as dead, as thou art apt to think: Take heed that they revive no more. The leaſt <hi>indulgence,</hi> or <hi>affection</hi> left behind, may renew inſenſibly, and grow great, and become big enough to bear thee down againſt thy preſent holy purpoſes, and become ſtrong enough to break down all the bonds of Reaſon and Religion; and then all thy Labour may prove to be loſt, thy guilt greater, and thy time leſs: So great are the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains of affection left for the old Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. O be then at leaſt more mindful of thy promiſes of obedience, than hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thou haſt been. Remember, that now thou haſt begun for Heaven, and ſet out for the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and undertaken, ſincerely to be for all that's holy juſt and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151744:64"/>good; and that now thou mayſt be ſafe for ever, holy and happy for ever, if pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and with an upright heart, thou carry on the concerns of thy Soul, with thoſe of thy allowable Calling, and to make them equally keep pace together, as thou art peacefully moving toward thy Prize and thy Crown: And as thou art thus going on chearfully to health and peace and pleaſure, look behind thee as little as thou canſt, leſt thy foot ſlip again, and thou loſe thy ground, and thy laſt ſtate be worſe than the firſt.</p>
               <p>Whenever therefore the old allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the old occaſions, and the former temptations ſhall return, or the Fleſh the World or the Devil, be ſtrongly draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee off, and preſſing thee to fall as groſly as ever, then (if poſſible) recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thy pious reſolutions, producing and laying them before thee, ſay, O my Soul, ſhall we now break them again? if we do, we know not, we are not ſure, that God will ever give us one advantage or opportunity more of a Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Now then is our time, of reſiſting the Enemies of our Saviour and our Soul, and of ſhowing what we can do for God and for Religion; for Heaven and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151744:64"/>Now, when our Enemies are moſt earneſt, buſie and importunate with us; let us now (ſeeing this is our time of tryal) gather up all our ſtrength, manage the Combat with Courage, and a great and fixt Reſolution, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the pleaſure, whatever the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage or Intereſt or Honour be, let us look on them all, as the flatteries of our Enemies, and be deaf to them all: and then (by Divine aid and aſſiſtance) We ſhall prevail, <hi>and be more than Conquerors. Rom.</hi> 8.37.</p>
               <p>And O my Soul, let it never be ſaid or remembred of us, in the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that we begun well very often, but perſevered not; went not on with alacrity and chearfulneſs, with Zeal and Courage in our pious Reſolutions. Never then let it be ſaid, that we forgot thee O Jeſu! forgot our League of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, our Covenant with thee, aſſoon as ever we came from Feaſting with thee.</p>
               <p>Should our Prince, whom we had high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provoked and injured by treaſonable words and actions, invite us to his Houſe, bid us come and dine with him at his own Table, ſhould he tell us he were willing to pardon us; willing to be reconcil'd
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151744:65"/>to us; notwithſtanding all the affronts and injuries he had offered him, willing to receive us into his embraces too, and to be (as we ſay) friends again, and take us to his favour; ſhould we not thankfully accept of the kindneſs? and be proud of the favour? Would it not melt us into Love and Affection, joy and gratitude? and upon this ſhould we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe him ſincerely to endeavour no more to partake with his Enemies, or to be lead by them to affront or diſpleaſe him; ſhould we, or could we indeed, aſſoon as ever we were gone out of his houſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently run to his Enemies and joyn with them, and fall to injuring him again as bad as ever, or perhaps worſe than ever? How diſingenuous, how provok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing muſt it needs be to him? If ſo, far be it from us my Soul, thus to deal with the King of Kings, and Prince of Peace, the Saviour of the World, and our dear Redeemer.</p>
               <p>But now when we go forth from his Houſe, the Houſe of Prayer, and are to apply our ſelves to the lawful Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and occaſions of this life, let us car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with us a faithful and conſtant remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of our holy purpoſes; and let this be one of our pious Reſolutions, no more
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151744:65"/>to be ever unmindful of the <hi>reſt</hi> of our good reſolutions which we made with God at the Holy Table.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Earneſtly beg of God to aſſiſt: thee in keeping any good Reſolutions, and in walking for the future in the ways of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Holyneſs.</hi> Our pious purpoſes, deſires, or intentions cannot be effected by our ſelves alone, without the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting and aſſiſting Grace of our Great Creator and Redeemer. Let us not fail then, frequently and earneſtly to ſue for it at the Throne of Grace; and then if we are not wanting to our own Intereſt, but with diligence and ſincerity, and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and honeſt endeavours, we ſet our ſelves to the performance of them, the day will e're long be ours, the Victory and the Crown ours.</p>
               <p>Say then, who would be ſo imprudent, as not earneſtly to ſue for that which he may certainly have for the asking and the uſing? and who would not diligently uſe and husband it, when the ſo doing will not fail to procure more? and then again, who would not induſtriouſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy that <hi>More,</hi> when (like Intereſt upon Intereſt) it would bring in more yet? St. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.12. and 25.29. St. <hi>Lu.</hi> 8.18. and 19.26.</p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:151744:66"/>
               <p>O let not the Grace of God be in vain, and loſt on us, only for want of our own Diligence in imploying and uſing it: and then let not our own watchfulneſs and labours and pious endeavours be all in vain, only for want of ſuing for the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of divine grace, frequently and devoutly beg of God therefore, to aid thee in all thy <hi>holy purpoſes and deſires and Reſolutions;</hi> that he will pleaſe to keep thee conſtant to them, as thou art paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing over this World, to him, and to a better; that he would increaſe the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of thy Sins, and the Love of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in thee, both which he has lately gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly begun in thee. Say to him, O my Lord, I have nothing, I am nothing, I can do nothing without thee; Theſe my Reſolutions and purpoſes of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, of piety and virtue, will up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the next violent Temptation be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering and tottering again, without thee and thy aid: By that be pleaſed to keep them warm and ſtedfaſt in me; ſo warm, that no length of time may cauſe them to grow cold again, no violence of a Temptation break through them.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Meditate on the guilt and the danger thou runneſt into, if thou la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour not more ſincerely afterward to keep
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151744:66"/>thoſe pious purpoſes; and thy Felicity if thou do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do not ſay, ſo to keep them as to live without Sin, and in an abſolutely perfect Eſtate; To live wholly without Sins of <hi>frailty</hi> and <hi>meer infirmity, ignorance or ſudden ſurprize,</hi> that is, thoſe that may ſometime or other ruſh on us e're we are a ware; No, but of not keeping thy Reſolutions of Reformation of all <hi>known cuſtomary wilful Sin</hi> whatever, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain no one ſuch known Iniquity.</p>
               <p>Remember, the Sin, if entertained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, at leaſt as familiarly as heretofore, and returned to with as much love as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, will now ever be a Sin againſt <hi>more Mercy, againſt more Love, and againſt more purpoſes and reſolutions</hi> of returning from it; O run not thy Soul then upon this increaſe of Guilt and Danger; But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>they ſay, O my Soul, ſhall we ſo ſoon forget our Lord, our Maſter Jeſus, to whom we lately vowed obedience, and ſwore Allegiance, as to entertain and cheriſh a known Enemy of his within our heart and boſome? Shall we ſoon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, whoſe <hi>ſighing, groaning, bleeding, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Love</hi> we have ſeen repreſented to us lately, and ſhall we add diſingenuity and ingratitude, and a vow-breach to the Sin
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151744:67"/>it ſelf? And ſhall we thus keep our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, and thus ſhew our endeavours to keep to our pious reſolutions, as tamely to yield up all, lay aſide all thoſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, at the return of the next Sin that looks pleaſantly, and that comes with fair opportunities for the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it? ſhall we do this, not only after ſo much love, but after having our Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant renewed and <hi>ſealed again</hi> with Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God? And after he has graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly declared, that he is willing to be reconciled to us, for what is paſt, if we heartily give up our ſelves to him for the future? and when we have promiſed ſo to do to our uttermoſt, and to give up the whole man to him?</p>
               <p>In ſum, ſhall we (ſay) in ſpight of ſo much Love, ſo much mercy and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, ſuch gracious offers on God's part; and then in ſpight of many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, purpoſes and reſolutions on ours, ſhall we return to our Luſts and Intemperance, as frequently as ever? to our old Oaths and Execrations, our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge and Malice, our Covetouſneſs and Injuſtice, our Pride or Ambition, our Inconſideration or Uncharitableneſs, to our darling Sin whatever it be? No, my Soul, we will now at laſt more ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151744:67"/>weigh the Guilt and Danger of ſo doing; We have begun, and let us go on for Eternity, whomſoever we diſpleaſe by it, whatever becomes of it as to this preſent life.</p>
               <p>Let us now once more conſider, that poſſibly this may be the laſt opportunity that our Saviour may give us to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd to him, before we go hence and be no more ſeen; the happy union and agreement between us has been lately ſealed, let us never more wilfully and knowingly break it, leſt all the old ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count be charged on us again. Let us therefore now make the beſt advantage, the beſt uſe of it we are able, and return no more to the former ſtate, leſt our Lord come and find us in ſuch a breach of our part of our Covenant, and never more permit us to renew it again, till the day of Judgment.</p>
               <p>And as now we have by our Lord's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercy, got a good advantage to try once more for a Crown of Life and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, let us be watchful and diligent, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied and conſtant in our Race, <hi>that our Lord when he comes, may find us ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Adieu then (ſay) once more my old <hi>Dalilahs,</hi> farewel to ye, and welcome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151744:68"/>welcome my holy Duties, ye that once ſeemed irkſome and tedious to me; Welcome now as the way and means by which I am to be qualified to have my Lord's merits applyed to me, to keep me in his favour, and to meet him in his Kingdome.</p>
               <p>Welcome my Devotions, ye that once ſeemed too tedious to me, and to take up too much of my time, the actions I once was even aſhamed to be found imployed in; Welcome, though purchaſed at ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo dear a rate, or expence of time, I am ſure I can be no loſer by you.</p>
               <p>Welcome my Solitudes and Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the World, and my frequent being alone; I find I can beſt ſee and conſider the ſtate of my Soul in ye, and though ye were once very diſagreeable to me, I now perceive you are advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious.</p>
               <p>Welcome ye Chriſtian Temperance and Sobriety, and Purity and Chaſtity, whatever ſelf-denials or reproaches ye may poſſibly coſt me, no matter, ſo I may ſit at the Feet of Jeſus to all Ages.</p>
               <p>And welcom Alms and Charity, though ye once ſeemed expenſive to me, and ill beſtown; I now ſee Cauſe, infinite Cauſe to think otherwiſe, when ye are laid
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:151744:68"/>out in order to the Inheritance of a Kingdome.</p>
               <p>Welcome Humility, Charity, and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs, and Love of Enemies, ye that once ſeemed unreaſonable, and of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Duties moſt diſagreeable to fleſh and blood, and a heavy yoke; but I now think otherwiſe of you, when I conſider how excellent an imitation ye are of that bleſſed Jeſus, with whom I lately ſupt, and at whoſe Feet I hope to ſit, in the manſions of Glory.</p>
               <p>Welcome Meekneſs and Patience, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification and Self-denyal, and all that's holy juſt and good. Welcome all means of my <hi>growth in Grace;</hi> all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of my Saviour; Welcome to me, who have reſolv'd never more to give out, never to think I have done enough, till all be over, and at an end, in a holy and happy Death in a bleſſed and joyful Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>Fifthly and Laſtly, <hi>after receiving; by looking back on this Divine and Heavenly and pleaſant Duty, think and meditate, how lovely and chearful and pleaſurable, a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Life must needs be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Say truely, is there not a great Sereni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Calm, and peace of mind, in the being free from Malice, and deſires of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:151744:69"/>Revenge, from Rage &amp; Envy? Is there not a Secret joy and Cheerfulneſs and Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeneſs of heart, in offering up Praiſes and Thankſgivings, and Hymns and Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujahs to the Saviour of the World? Is there not a bleſſed inward Reliſh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and pleaſure that flows from the offering up a holy and devout Prayer to him? How great a ſatisfaction and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſs is there in offering up ſome of our ſubſtance to God in Alms? Is there not a great quiet and ſedateneſs, and peace of Soul and mind, in the being free from the hurries, and the ſhame and follies, and ſollicitations of Luſtful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires? Is there not an unknown tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of mind in the being freed from proud and vain-glorious and ambitious deſires, and in the ſitting down at eaſe with meekneſs, contentment and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity? Is it not a bleſſed thing to be freed from the pain and diſorders of Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance? from the ſhame and diſhonour of Luſt? to have ſubdued, and conquered, and mortified our paſſions and ſinful ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, and to ſit above the reach of them? Muſt it not needs be a bliſsful thing, to be freed from thoſe ſtings and laſhings and ſecret gnawings, that perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually dwell in the heart of the wicked,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:151744:69"/>and irreligious man? though they are little known to any other but God and his own Soul? Is it not (think you) a great felicity to be freed from the ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Sin and the Devil, which are the greateſt Tyrants in the World? Can you not now from this ſhort and ſmall experience of theſe things, be perſwaded of the <hi>ſweets</hi> and <hi>Delicacies</hi> that dwell with Religion?</p>
               <p>Do but ask the holy perſon, the man of an heavenly Converſation, whether there ever be any thing that greatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſes and troubles his ſerene and calm, and peaceful heart? Ask him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, whether he do not each night lye down in peace, and with an undiſturbed Conſcience, ſleep ſweetly and ſecurely, content heartily if his Lord pleaſe, to ſleep 'till the general Reſurrection? Ask him, whether he, lying down in peace and Innocence, feels the inſupportable horror and amazement of any great guilt when he awakes? No, he awakes as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly as the morning, he no ſooner o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens his Eyes, but they are darted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> before they behold vanities.</p>
               <p>Ask him whether he dreads the Face of the Sun, or Men or Devils? Whether
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151744:70"/>he greatly dreads the ſight of an open Grave, of a winding Sheet, or the name of Death? Know of the pious Soul a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, whither there be any real pleaſures in a holy retired, and angelical life? and he will tell you, he has found more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in being a devout communicant at his Lord's Table, than ever he found in the commiſſion of the moſt reliſhing Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. Ask him further, whether thoſe pleaſures do not ſtay longer with him, than any others? and he muſt undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly tell you, that as <hi>the pleaſures of Sin are but for a ſmall Seaſon,</hi> none of them laſting and continuing; So thoſe of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are permanent and abiding.</p>
               <p>But now on the other head. Let us a little enquire into the unpeaceful, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant ſtate of the unholy perſon. Ask him, whether when he is ſometimes in the midſt of his jollities and pleaſures, there do not ſomething within him check and reſtrain the freedome of his mirth? and often on a ſudden turn him into fears and Melancholy? and if he would ſpeak the truth, he muſt needs confeſs, that he hath been frequently ſerved ſo. Alas! this is his guilty Conſcience, proceeding from his inconſiderate ſtate of life; this is the fruit and effect of his Crimes, and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151744:70"/>the want of a more frequent and devout communicating.</p>
               <p>Enquire of him again, whether he uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally lyes down in peace and reſt? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he do not often ſtartle in his ſleep, and his very dreams are not terrible? whether he be not hugely apt to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted and diſcompoſed, and diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to fear almoſt every little noiſe, and at laſt awakes with unknown horrors of Guilt upon his heart? This he can doubtleſs tell you is a ſad truth.</p>
               <p>Ask of him again, whether, when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers take their innocent recreations, and refreſh their Spirits with harmleſs mirth; whither (I ſay) he do not ſometimes ſigh and droop, and goes away alone, withdraws into ſome ſolitary place, and is there diſcontented, full of anguiſh, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plext and haunted, and when he hears the knel of his departed Neighbours, looks pale, and trembles; and is amazed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo little prepared for the ſame ſtate and condition?</p>
               <p>Ask him, whether, when he beholds a dead Corps, his blood do not cool and ſurround his heart? Alas! poor wretch, 'tis his guilty Conſcience, his Sins unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of, his life unreformed, that are the Cauſes of theſe doleful and diſmal
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151744:71"/>Confuſions; and little (it may be) do the World think, the Iniquities he knows himſelf guilty of. This, if he would confeſs, he muſt needs acknowledge.</p>
               <p>Say, now, is it not a bleſſed Eſtate of life, to be alwayes freed, and to ſit at a diſtance from theſe? to be at peace from theſe ſecret tumults and inward horrors? Why, 'tis Religion and holyneſs, and frequent communions alone, that can ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it for us.</p>
               <p>Say again, when we look back on the ſtate and temper of the pious man, can we chooſe but think it a bleſt and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing, alway to have the Soul in that diſpoſition? why, 'tis Piety and Virtue, That can alone fix and ſettle that joy and peace there.</p>
               <p>To which ſtate, when you are once (by the aſſiſtance of Heaven) arrived, you will find reaſon to ſay, O my Soul, how much peace and joy do we find in that State of Life, in which we have reaſon to hope our Lord is reconciled to us? How much better is it, how exceedingly beyond the old unreformed, unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate courſe? how ſweet is the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of being become from an <hi>Enemy, a friend of God? and to think that we have cauſed joy in Heaven by our returning?</hi> Oh
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151744:71"/>how imprudent were we, that we ſhould believe nothing of thoſe things ſooner, and could not be brought to believe there was any ſuch contentment and joy in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs!</p>
               <p>How many Dayes and Months and Years of true Peace and Pleaſure have we loſt, that we had not been acquainted with our Saviour ſooner? That the voice of God, inwardly calling us, often by his holy Spirit, or outwardly by his Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors, ſhould ſo long have been in vain? Oh that we ſhould not have been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by them to come ſooner; <hi>and to taſt and ſee, how gracious the Lord is.</hi> — That we ſhould ſcarce ever till now, find by our own Experience, that the wayes of Religious Wiſdom, <hi>are wayes of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſs, and all her paths are peace.</hi> Prov. 3.17.</p>
               <p>But bleſſed be God, that he has at laſt opened our Eyes to behold the wonderful things of his Law,<note place="margin">Pſ. 119.18.</note> and enclined us to expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and try the ſweetneſs, pleaſure and ſatisfaction, of being in a good meaſure qualified to have his merits applied to us; that he has given us Grace to experience ſomewhat of the bliſsful apprehenſions of being in his Favour.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:151744:72"/>
               <p>And now O my Soul, what infinite reaſon have we to ſay, Bleſſed be the day that ever we came acquainted with our Saviour! Bleſſed be the day that ever our diſobedient heart was melted into Love of thee, O our dear Redeemer! And I beſeech thee, keep it filled ever with this love, fortified ever with theſe Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ever fixt and conſtant in this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; and if there be any thing in it, that yet may diſpleaſe thee, O make me to know it, and aſſiſt me to throw it off for ever!</p>
               <p>And when will our Lord come again? that we may again Sup with him, and feaſt our ſelves upon his ſacred Body and Blood, and taſt this pleaſant, moſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious food again? May he <hi>make no long tarrying,</hi> may it not be long, O may it not be long, before we again either meet him at his Table, meet him in the Air, or meet him in his Kingdom. O what will it be to be always with him, where there is ſo much ſecret joy and peace, in this ſmall glymps of him, and at ſo great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance too!</p>
               <p>And now my Soul, ſeeing we have given up our heart to our deareſt Lord; in this temper let us live, and in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition let us dye; and we hope by
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:151744:72"/>Death we ſhall come nearer to him, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more to be pulled back again, or in danger to be drawn off from him by the violence of any temptation; for theſe ſhall be done away. And being thus united to him the great Lover of Souls, we ſhall at laſt, at his glorious coming, not much dread the <hi>heavens being rolled into a Scroul,</hi> or the Crack and flames of the dying World, or the Trump of the Arch-angel; but with infinite joy, hear the words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſe, &amp; come up hither;</hi> awake, and ariſe, and come, Take your Crowns, your place on my right hand. Ariſe, and come and ſee your new State, and new Condition; your unknown felicities, and unknown Glories, your endleſs peace and ſafety.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſe and come hither,</hi> up to me your Jeſus the <hi>Captain of your Salvation;</hi> Come, and be above the reach of Infelicities and Miſeries, Sin and Death for all ages; and ſit down in your Immortality and Reſt for ever. Ariſe, come and partake of thoſe Glories, that coſt me your Lord, Sighs, and Groans, and Blood, and Wounds, pangs and Life it ſelf, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it for you: that coſt you alſo ſo many Dutys; the Strugling with ſo
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151744:73"/>many temptations, the combating ſo many Enemies, before you got the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; ſo many difficulties, diſcouragements, ſo much ſhame and reproach, ſelf-denials, and the like, before you were intitled to my Merits, and qualified to receive the bene t of my purchaſe; Come now, and ſit down in their Enjoyment, for above millions of years and ages.</p>
               <p>In a word, O my Soul, ſay, May theſe hopes be ever in our view, ever in our heart &amp; thoughts. And as we have lately begun for Eternity, upon the Stock of this Hope; ſo let us by this ſquare and order all the Actions of our lives: That ſo at laſt, when we ſhall come to leave Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, our Paſſage hence may be peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſafe, and holy; our Reſurrection joyfull, ſafe and holy: and (through him who is the foundation of our hope) we may not fail to be remembred with mercy in the day of judgment. After which, we may with <hi>Angels, and Arch-Angels, and all the Company of Heaven, laud and magnify his glorious Name, ever more praiſing him, and Saying Holy, Holy, Holy Lord God of Hoſts, Glory be to the, O Lord moſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> High,</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:151744:73"/>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer before the holy Sacrament.</head>
               <p>O My deareſt Saviour, who wert pleaſed to ſuffer death upon the Croſs, to purchaſe Heaven and Salvation for me, and now calleſt me to a remembrance of that thy dying Love; ſo fit and trim, and adorn my Soul I beſeech thee, that I may not fail, to be now and ever an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable gueſt at thy holy Table.</p>
               <p>Let the conſideration of my ſtate, and the remembrance of my paſt ſins, lead me to a deep humiliation and contrition for them, and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition to intire hatred, a ſincere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of them, and fixt reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of future Love and obedience. O my Saviour, let my Faith, and Charity, and Devotion be, by thy gracious aſſiſtance, raiſed to a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:151744:74"/>pitch and temper; that ſo, whatever thou pleaſe to deny me in this lower World, I may never be denied a participation of all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of thy meritorious death and ſufferings. I come dear Jeſu, I come to renew my Covenant with thee, which I have ſo miſerably broken, by my Sins of Omiſſion and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, by my Iniquities of thought word and deed,<note n="†" place="margin">Here you may mention thoſe groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Crimes which upon Examination, you find your ſelf to ſtand guilty of.</note> [particularly by my Sins of —] For theſe and all other my impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, known and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, be pleaſed to receive a reconciliation: and let this holy Sacrament prove a ſealing of my Pardon in the Court of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and may I not fail, O my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, together with thy body and blood, to receive new Grace and ſtrength againſt them. O my Jeſu, who haſt done and ſuffered ſo much for me, and now inviteſt me to come
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:151744:74"/>and ſee it repreſented to me, be pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do this further for me, to grant that it may not be in vain and loſt as to me, by mine own default. O let it never be ſaid or remembred of me in the day of Judgment, that I ever appeared before thee in this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly action, without ſuch a wedding Garment, as thou didſt mercifully accept; or that I did eat and drink my own damnation. And though my Iniquities are great; great like thy Sorrows, and great like thy ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, which I am coming to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate; yet becauſe they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely leſs than thy Mercies and thy Merits; Pitty me, O Lord pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty me, accept me, O my God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept me, for lo I come to do thy will; and grant that I may ever hereafter live the life of Grace, in a ſtate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to thee; that ſo by thine Agony and bloody ſweat, by thy Croſs and Paſſion, by thy precious death and burial, by thy glorious Reſurrection and Aſcention, which I
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:151744:75"/>am coming to remember, my paſt Iniquities being done away, I may now at length be more cloſely uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thee. That I may come back again from thy Table with joy and thanks, and Love and adoration, and comfort and ſatisfaction. O that at laſt my Reſolutions may be fixt, and ſtedfaſt; the conqueſt of theſe Sins which I can eaſily remember have often foiled me, may be ſuch, that they may no more prevail againſt me, and get the Dominion over me. And that now thou mayeſt abide with me forever, and the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit may guide me into the paths of a cheerful, ſincere, and perſevering Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs; that ſo having paſt my days that are to come, in the watchfulneſs and diligence, and Labours of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and a holy Life; I may live with thee, and dye with thee, and riſe again with thee, and then ever ſit at thy Feet in the manſions of Glory, O my deareſt Saviour, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:151744:75"/>
               <head>A Thankſgiving and Prayer after Receiving.</head>
               <p>OHoly and Eternal Jeſu; I praiſe thee, I bleſs thee, I worſhip thee, I glorifie thee, I give thee thanks for thoſe invaluable mercies from the participation of which I lately came; for theſe repreſentations of thy bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, dying love to me; Love infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, Love unſpeakable, Love eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, Love for me before I was born. O compaſſionate Jeſu! who am I, that thou ſhouldeſt pleaſe to receive me, to renew my part of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace with thee, who have ſo frequently, ſo miſerably broken it? O let the return which now I may ever hereafter make, for ſo much love, let it be Love and Obedience. Love, in ſome meaſure great like thine, even to death it ſelf; and let my Obedience be as early as I can now make it, and as chearful and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal, ſincere and conſtant. O let
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151744:76"/>the deep remembrance of this Love of thine, conſtrain me to ſuch an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, Let neither the Love of the World, the allurements and baits of the fleſh, or the temptations of the Devil, ever force or draw me off from ſuch an obedience. O my dear Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, though I have now again reſolved againſt all wilful known Sin, [particularly againſt the Sin of<note n="†" place="margin">Here you may mention the Sin to which you are moſt tempted.</note> —] and promiſed thee an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the continuance of thy gracious aid and aſſiſtance, I ſhall moſt certainly fall again, upon the very next temptation. Secure me therefore O Lord, by that, ſecure me, ſave Lord or I periſh: Whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thou pleaſeſt to deny me here, deny me not, I beſeech thee O Lord, I beſeech thee, the aſſiſtance of that Grace of thine, without which, my Spiritual Enemies will ſoon prevail over me again. Make me to ſee and conſider, the neceſſity of avoiding all
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:151744:76"/>appearance of evil, all thoſe occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of my falling, and to get inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the way of Sin, whatever I am like to loſe by it, whatever the diſadvantage be in this World: Let, O let my Sacramental vows, and promiſes, and Reſolutions, be never ſo broken again, as they have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time been formerly; but O my Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, let my Sins and Iniquities ever hereafter appear ſo odious, and hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to me, as they did then when I was at my Lord's Table. O let them ſtill be as vile and deformed as they then ſeemed to me. Let none of my pious purpoſes, and holy Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, be ever forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by me [particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly.<note n="†" place="margin">Here again, if you think fit, you may mention any holy Reſolution made by you.</note> —] Let neither the cares of the World, nor the diſappointments of my expectations in the affairs of it; nor the malice of my Enemies, the charitable reproofs of my friends, the treſpaſſes of my Neighbours, the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151744:77"/>hardneſs of my Labours, the Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity and earneſtneſs of my Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, the neglects and injuſtices of my Debtors, any fears of being poor, any diſtruſts concerning a proviſion, for my poſterity; or my being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed or reproached by any man, or my Loſſes of the World, nor that World of Temptations, through which I know I am to paſs, ever put my Soul out of frame, or lead me to a diſcontented, inconſiderate, and troubled Spirit, or put my holy pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes out of my mind: but that in the midſt of theſe and all other tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults of the World, I may alway fly to Religion, and take Sanctuary there, and be ſafe and reſt there, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to do thy will, and be ready to offer up my Soul and Body to thy Service. That ſo the reſt of my dayes that are yet to come in this World may be paſſed away in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and Charity, in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and holineſs, in mortification and ſelf-denial, in love and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:151744:77"/>to thee O holy and Eternal Jeſu. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A pious Reſolution, which may be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly made (on their Knees) by them, who ſince their Baptiſm, have had no opportunity to be confirmed by the Biſhop: but yet <hi>(being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and deſirous to be confirmed)</hi> are willing to receive the Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</head>
               <p>DRead Majeſty of Heaven and Earth! — Foraſmuch as thou haſt received me in my Baptiſm in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Covenant of Grace, (ſealed by the blood of Jeſus) when an Infant; Lord, I being now come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it, do on my bended knees humbly and thankfully own and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that infinite favour, and adore thy mercy. And do really and heartily take upon my ſelf, what was then engaged for me, and by the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:151744:78"/>help of thy Grace, (which I earneſtly beg) do reſolve to perform with an hearty ſincerity my part of that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, to the end of my dayes. I believe what was then promiſed I ſhould believe, Lord help my unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. I renounce in my own perſon, what was then promiſed I ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce. And for the conditions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired on my part, (to wit) a joynt performance of all the Goſpel-Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Duties, as Faith, Hope, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Self-denyal, Repentance, and the reſt, and an obedience to all of them in ſincerity, thô with weakneſs and Imperfection; Lord, I humbly and thankfully embrace and accept of them, and declare my hearty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and reſolutions to diſcharge them acceptably, through the holy Jeſus. And before thee O holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and the whole Court of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, I do ſolemnly make this Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and renew my Baptiſmal Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant Promiſe and Engagement. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:151744:78"/>
               <p>If you are able to write, you may write out a Copy of theſe Words; and having repeated them before God with a deep humility and pious affections, you may add theſe words to it, [<hi>and ſign it on my bended knees</hi>] And then before you riſe, ſubſcribe your name to it, and the day of the month.</p>
               <p>January 1. 1681. N. N.</p>
               <p>Ever after remembring, that now you have dedicated your ſelf to God, and that if you live the reſt of your life according to theſe beginnings, your paſſing over the World ſhall be ſafe and holy; and you be intituled to the Merits of your Redeemer, and qualified to receive the benefits of his death and ſufferings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:151744:79"/>
               <head>An act of Reſolution which may be humbly and devoutly made on their knees, by thoſe who ſince their laſt receiving the holy Sacrament, have (through the violence of a Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and it's daily ſolicitation, though conſtantly reſiſted) ſometime fallen into ſome one act of known wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sin.</head>
               <p>DRead Majeſty of Heaven and Earth. Foraſmuch as I, who was early dedicated to thee by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and have frequently renewed that Covenant at thy holy Table, have yet ſadly fallen from my Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal holyneſs, and broken my vows and reſolutions even ſince the laſt Sacrament, grieving thy holy Spirit, wounding my Soul, and provoking thy diſpleaſure, ſetting my ſelf back deplorably in my jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney toward Heaven, by the Sin of<note n="†" place="margin">Here you may mention the Sin.</note> —] beſt known to thee when and where com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted:
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:151744:79"/>I do now heartily accuſe and judge, and condemn my ſelf for it, and for all other known and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Sins; and do earneſtly repent my ſelf of it, and deſire to riſe from it again by a ſincere Reſolution of amendment of life, a greater watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and intire obedience; and this I ſolemnly on my bended knees de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare before thee O holy Trinity: and do now likewiſe humbly beg freſh aſſiſtances of the holy Spirit to enable me to be more conſtant in my holy Reſolutions, and to pleaſe thee better. And for my Lord Jeſus ſake, and in his Name, and for thy loves ſake to mankind, thy pitty and compaſſions ſake, humbly beg, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly hope, my pardon may be as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly now ſealed in Heaven, as I make this declaration here on earth. Mercy O my God, mercy, for the ſake of that immaculate Lamb, that takes away the Sins of the World, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:151744:80"/>
               <p>Here again, if you are able to write, and ſincerely do deſire to riſe from the Sin by Repentance, you may before you go to the holy Table, write out a Copy of theſe Words; and having repeated them with a penitent heart, ſubſcribe your name on your bended knees, as alſo the day when you made this Reſolution.</p>
               <p>January 1. 1681. N. N.</p>
               <p>That ſo you may the better diſcern, what progreſs your ſoul makes, in its Victory over all known Sin.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>For no man can well obſerve his own growth in Grace,<note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi> Rule of holy dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> but by accounting ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domer returns of Sin, and a more frequent victory over tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; concerning which every man makes his obſervations, according as he makes his inquiries and ſearch after himſelf.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:151744:80"/>
               <head>A Prayer before the Sacrament; which may be uſed by them, who never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it before.</head>
               <p>O Bleſſed Saviour and Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er! who wert pleaſed to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> me into thy holy Church by the Waters of Baptiſm in my Infant dayes before I knew it; I do now, being by thy Grace come to the knowledge of it, from the bottom of my heart adore and bleſs thee for that mercy, and with a penitent heart, humbly and earneſtly beg thy pardon for my great abuſes of it, that I ſhould ſo wretchedly as I have, ſtained and poluted thoſe white and innocent Robes which I then put on; and for my known and unknown breaches of thoſe vows and promiſes, which were then made in my name. O my Lord, I am accuſed, judged and condemned by my own Conſcience. But O my Jeſu, whoſe ſacred ſide once dropt Water and Blood for me;
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:151744:81"/>as thou haſt admitted me to the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when I was baptized, ſo be thou now graciouſly pleaſed to admit me to the Blood too, and to partake of all the benefits of it, that as I early partaked of the cleanſing of the one, ſo I may now receive the healing vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the other; and let all my Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities I beſeech thee, that have been adventured on by me ſince my Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm to this preſent hour, be to thee as if they had never been at all. O that I could now go to thy Table with the like innocence that I came from the waters of Regeneration; But ſeeing I cannot, O my Jeſu, who wert pleas'd to bring me to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and priviledge of Baptiſm, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I could beg or deſire it, be thou likewiſe pleaſed, by thy grace to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry me prepared to thy Table, who can, and do earneſtly deſire and beg this of thee; and as thou wert plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed then to make me a lamb of thy flock, ſo deny me not the favour (how unworthy ſoever I have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:151744:81"/>lived of it) of being one of thoſe faithful Sheep of thy fold, that hear thy voice. O my Lord, as I was never yet at thy Table, and come a ſtranger to this Heavenly feaſt; ſo I intreat thee, let me not miſs of the mercy of being a wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and acceptable gueſt there. O make me to underſtand and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the advantage that I have above many others, who may now (by thy Grace) never be an unworthy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant. Do thou therefore by thy gracious interceſſion ſupply my ignorance, and by thy Mercy and Merits, pitty and pardon the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and ſins and follies of my youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſtate, [particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note n="†" place="margin">Here you may mention the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</note>—] and receive me with the Love and Compaſſion and Tenderneſs of a Parent: that ſo I may love thee, and adore thee, and bleſs thee, and obey thee betimes; and may taſt of the ſweets and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacies of an early Religion and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs.
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:151744:82"/>I come then O my Jeſu, I come to give thee this firſt ſolemn Teſtimony of my Love to thee, and to receive the firſt great tokens of thy Love to me. O be pleaſed ſo feelingly to touch my heart now at the firſt with a deep ſence of Love to thee and thy Religion, that I may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hereafter rejoyce in all opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of a holy Sacrament, and have a never-ceaſing Love to thoſe holy Myſteries. Do thou vouchſafe O my dear Redeemer, at this our firſt moſt ſolemn meeting, to bring all thoſe Graces along with thee, which thou would'ſt have my Soul to be fitted with, and fix them there I beſeech thee. O my Lord I was early de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to thee by others, but ſuffer me now to dedicate my ſelf to thee. Come Lord Jeſu, come then, take poſſeſſion of my heart, I beſeech thee, before ever the World, Fleſh, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, get any more footing there; and if either of them have got any alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, for my great neglects to preſent
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:151744:82"/>my ſelf to thee, and opening the door of it to thee ſooner, turn out, O my Lord turn them out thence, and with the reſt of thy Church accept me, even me alſo O my Father. Let me take thee into my hand, O my dear Lord, and place thee in my heart, before ever any more luſts or follies be admitted there; and then be thou pleaſed to take me by the hand, and place me in thy heart, that there I may live, and there I may dye. Finally O my Lord, let all my paſt Iniquities I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, be ſo done away, that thou mayſt receive me ſo, as if I were but now come from the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>With ſuch hopes as theſe, with ſuch defires as theſe, I come to lay my ſelf at thy feet, O bleſſed Saviour and Redeemer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:151744:83"/>
               <head>A Prayer and Thankſgiving after the holy Sacrament, to be uſed only by ſuch, as had never received it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</head>
               <p>O Holy and merciful Jeſus! by whom the mercies of Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are conveyed to mankind; I bleſs and praiſe and thank thee, with my whole heart, and all the powers of my Soul, for this firſt admittance of me to the mercy and the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Holy Sacrament of thy Body and Blood; for my having lately partaked of ſome of theſe joyes and comforts that are alone to be found with thee and in thy Service, and till now were unknown to me.</p>
               <p>O that having had the mercy and advantage of renewing my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with thee, I may now at leaſt begin to ſpend my days, (as far as ever the neceſſary buſineſs of this preſent life will permit me) in thy Service, in all the parts of piety and
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:151744:83"/>virtue; in works of Mercy and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Devotion, in meekneſs and humility, in ſelf-denial and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, in Chaſtity and Temperance, in all that's holy juſt and good. O my Lord! 'tis the ſerious deſire and reſolution of my Soul thus to do; that ſo early beginning to lay up my treaſure in Heaven, I may (by thy Grace) have a good account there in the Records of Eternity, at the end of my ſixty or ſeventy years. O my Jeſu! whatever thou pleaſeſt elſe to deny me here, deny me not a grant of this my requeſt I beſeech thee; that thoſe deſires and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of mine, may in ſome good meaſure be accompliſhed and effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Let not the allurements and perſwaſions of my Companions, ever entice me from my Duty, or the jeers or reproaches of any man what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, fright me from my Innocence. O let me never ſuffer my ſelf to be laught out of my Religion, or be aſhamed or affraid to perform my
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:151744:84"/>holy Duties before the face of any man, but be ever looking unto Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; and let me in view of him be content to endure the Croſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the ſhame, or whatever elſe ſhall befal me for the ſake of Piety and Virtue, or obedience to any one Command of thine: Let my youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful heart be never much inflam'd with any Loves, or paſſions or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, but thoſe of thee and thy holy Religion. O my Lord, grant, that I may be perſwaded to underſtand and conſider, what a great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage I have, of devoting and giving up my firſt and beſt dayes to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Piety; and that now is my time to ſhew, that I am lead to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by Love, and by my choice, and not driven to it only by the fears and horrors of an approaching Grave: and that I may often and betimes conſider, with how much greater comfort I ſhall leave Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, if I may be able then to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber an early Love and Obedience to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:151744:84"/>thee O Jeſu. Let me who have liv'd in thy family ever ſince I was baptized, now at leaſt begin to feel my ſelf more powerfully drawn to thee than ever. O make me in the beginning of my dayes, to be true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerious and conſiderate; to begin to withdraw from the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and to love to be ſometime alone, to look into the ſtate of my Soul, and provide for a joyful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. Make me to think it the greateſt happineſs in this World to chooſe thee O bleſſed Jeſu, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for my Lord and Maſter, and to look on Religion as the Reſt and Delight, and Satisfaction of my Soul. O fill my Soul with ſuch a Love to thee, and to thoſe holy Myſteries in which I commemorate a dying Lord, that I may be able to think it long, before I have an opportunity to come to feaſt upon thy Body and Blood again; and that as I grow in years, I may in ſome meaſure grow in Grace, and in the Divine favour.
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:151744:85"/>To this end, O that I may paſs ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through this dangerous ſtate of life, freed from the Intemperance and Luſts, the folly and vanity, the heedleſneſs and inconſideration, that often attends it: and that I may the better be able thus to do, Lord I now deliver up to thee, all my Affections and Deſires, to be guided and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by thy Holy Spirit; I am willing to ſubmit them all to thee, that ſo as I have lately begun for Eternity, I may go on, and proſper, and in an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable meaſure, now keep up to the purity and Innocence of my firſt ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, and never more give out, till I come to the end of my hopes, and the beginning of my joyes, and be preſented to my Father, pure and ſpotleſs, in the great day of Rewards and Puniſhments, by thee O holy and merciful Jeſus, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:151744:85"/>
               <head>A Prayer which may be uſed by them, who before they come to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſet apart ſomething to be then offered up to God in Alms.</head>
               <p>O Merciful Lord! from whom every good gift comes, and by whoſe bounty alone it is, that I enjoy any thing which I poſſeſs; I humbly offer up this ſmall return of it to thee, for the uſe of them whom thou haſt made thy receivers, the poor and the needy. Let not the ſmalneſs of the offering, or any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthyneſs of mine, I beſeech thee, keep it from being an acceptable Alms and Oblation to thee; and let not the abuſe of any of my poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that have been laid out on Sin and Folly, Gluttony or Vanity, Luſt or Intemperance, Revenge or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, be ever charged or remembred againſt me, in the day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And O my God take from me a Covetous and Illiberal heart,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:151744:86"/>and teach me the truely Chriſtian meaſures of Charity, in Giving, and Forgiving for Jeſus ſake, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:151744:86"/>
               <head>A Prayer for the Grace of Charity in forgiving, with particular reference to that petition in our Lord's Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, [forgive us our treſpaſſes as we forgive, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] which may be uſed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before the Sacrament, or any other time.</head>
               <p>O Bleſſed and holy Jeſus! who wert the great Example of Giving and Forgiving, dying for Enemies, ready and willing to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give Iniquity and Sin, and to give Heaven and Glory to all true Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents; Give me Grace to write after all this bleſſed Copy of thine in an acceptable meaſure. And if there be, or has been any offender or treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer againſt me, whom I have not forgiven, according to thy Will, and the meaſures of the Goſpel, forgive me O bleſſed Jeſu, and let me not fail to receive a full pardon of that Iniquity, for thy mercies ſake. O let my deſires and Petitions of being
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:151744:87"/>forgiven as I forgive, never be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered according to that inſtance whatſoever it were, or ever ſhall be, wherein I have not heretofore, or (through the frailty of humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or any ſudden ſurprize or incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration) ſhould not hereafter at any time, keep up to thy ſacred Rule and Will. And O Lord guide and direct me for the Remainder of my dayes in the true meaſures of Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and forbearance, and take from me all malice and hatred, and grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and heart-burnings, and deſires of Revenge on any that has injured me; and plant in my Soul, I humbly and earneſtly beſeech thee, the true Charity and forgiveneſs. O Lord, for thy mercies ſake, thy Love's ſake to mankind, ſo pitty me, and pardon all my former gratifications of my revengeful humour, that they may never be ſo charged on me or remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, as to hinder thy forgiveneſs of me: And whomſoever, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſoever I have forgiven any, freely
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:151744:87"/>and fully and truely, be thou pleaſed O my dear Redeemer, that all my former, and all my future petitions may be heard and granted, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that inſtance; And whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I have already, or ever ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to be forgiven as I forgive, O merciful Lord, forgive me, as I then forgive. And grant, that for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture I may ſo Copy out the bleſſed pattern which thou haſt left me, that no Enemies, Perſecuters, Slanderers, Revilers, or Injurious Perſons, may ever be able to conquer my love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them:<note place="margin">Chriſt. Sacrif.</note> 
                  <q>But that I may ſtill bear a kind and tender heart to the moſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged and provoking Spirits, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thoſe that curſe me, praying for thoſe who deſpightfully uſe me, returning Courteſies for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts and injuries; bewailing their Sins, pittying their miſeries, and endeavouring to overcome evil with good. Endow me with ſuch a wiſe, conſidering, and ſober Spirit, that I
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:151744:88"/>may ever prefer the example of thee my Lord and Maſter, before all the Cuſtoms and faſhions of this World: Enduring the mockeries, the ſhame and contempt which may be caſt upon me, for the following his forgiveneſs and patience. And do thou. O God, to whom venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance belongeth, pardon alſo and forgive thoſe by whom I ſuffer wrongfully; Spare them good Lord, ſpare them, and deny them not the Grace of Repentance, that we may live together in eternal Love and Friendſhip with thee, O bleſſed and holy Jeſus.</q> 
                  <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father, which art in Heaven; Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed be thy Name. Thy kingdom come. Thy will be done in earth, As it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily bread. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us our treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation; But deliver us from evil: for thine is the Kingdom, And the Power, And the Glory, For ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bookseller_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:151744:88"/>
            <head>The Bookseller to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THE abſence of the Author, and his inconvenient diſtance from <hi>London,</hi> hath occaſioned theſe <hi>Erra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi>'s to eſcape the Preſs. The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thinks it the beſt inſtance of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, if his Eſcapes be not laid upon the Author, and he hopes they are no greater than an ordinary under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding may amend, and a little cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity may forgive.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. Royſton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. line 5. for <hi>tanta,</hi> read <hi>tacita:</hi> p. 11. l. 9. for <hi>as,</hi> r. <hi>all:</hi> p. 14. l. 27. r. <hi>perform it:</hi> p. 31. l. 30. r. <hi>ſaid do this. If:</hi> p. 33. l. 13. for <hi>lifted,</hi> r. <hi>liſted:</hi> p. 33. l. 20. r. <hi>a ſolemn:</hi> p. 35. l. 4. r. <hi>to come:</hi> p. 39. l. 12. for <hi>could,</hi> r. <hi>would:</hi> p. 46. l. 21. dele <hi>to:</hi> p. 48. l. 9. for <hi>never,</hi> r. <hi>ever:</hi> l. 22. dele <hi>I:</hi> p. 99. l. 23. for <hi>great,</hi> r. <hi>dangerous:</hi> p. 100. l. 5. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le <hi>to:</hi> p. 112. l. 17. for <hi>head,</hi> r. <hi>hand:</hi> p. 116. l. 23. for <hi>where,</hi> r. <hi>when:</hi> p. 147. l. 9. r. <hi>forgave:</hi> l. 17. r. <hi>enraged.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:151744:89"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151744:89"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> Bookſeller to His moſt Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</head>
            <p>ΕΙΚΩΝ ΒΑΣΙΛΙΚΗ: The Pourtraicture of His Sacred Majeſty King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of ever bleſſed Memory; in his Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes and Sufferings, newly reprint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by His Majeſtie's ſpecial Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s Annotations on the New Teſtament, in <hi>Folio,</hi> the Fifth Edition, Corrected.</p>
            <p>The Book of Pſalms Paraphraſed, with Arguments to each Pſalm, in Two Volumes: by <hi>S. Patrick,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Peterburgh,,</hi> and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain in Ordinary to His Majeſty. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Truth of Chriſtian Religion, in Six Books, written in Latin by <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> and now Tranſlated into Engliſh, with the addition of a
<pb facs="tcp:151744:90"/>Seventh Book: by <hi>S. Patrick,</hi> D. D. <hi>&amp;c. Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Book for Beginners; or, A help to young Communicants, that they may be fitted for the holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and receive it with profit: by <hi>S. Patrick,</hi> D. D. in 24<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>Chriſt's Counſel to his Church; in two Sermons preached at the two laſt Faſts: by <hi>S. Patrick,</hi> D. D. in <hi>Quarto,</hi> new.</p>
            <p>The Eſtabliſh'd Church; or, A Subverſion of all the Romaniſt's Pleas for the Popes Supremacy in <hi>England:</hi> together with a Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the preſent Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as allow'd by the Laws of the Land, againſt all Fanatical Exceptions: particularly of Mr. <hi>Hickeringill,</hi> in his ſcandalous Pamphlet, ſtiled <hi>NAKED TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH,</hi> the Second Part: by <hi>Fran. Fulwood,</hi> D. D. Archdeacon of <hi>Totnes</hi> in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>von:</hi> in <hi>Octavo,</hi> new.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of the Morality of the Sabbath: being an Expoſition of
<pb facs="tcp:151744:90"/>
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9, 10, 11. Humbly offer'd to this preſent Age: by <hi>John Gregory,</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> in <hi>Octavo,</hi> new.</p>
            <p>The New Diſtemper; or, The Diſſenters uſual Pleas for Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, Toleration, and the Renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Covenant, Conſider'd and Diſcuſs'd; with ſome Reflexions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s and Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi>'s late Pamphlets, publiſhed in Anſwer to the Reverend Dean of <hi>S. Paul</hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon concerning Separation: by the late Reverend Dr. <hi>Tomkins,</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lively Picture of <hi>Lewis du Moulin,</hi> drawn by an incomparable Hand: together with his Laſt Words, being his <hi>Retractation</hi> of all the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Reflexions he had made on the Divines of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) in ſeveral Books of his) Signed by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf on the Fifth and Seventeenth of <hi>October,</hi> 1680. in <hi>Quarto,</hi> new.</p>
            <p>The daily practice of Devotion; or, The hours of Prayer, fitted to the main Uſes of a Chriſtian Life, with
<pb facs="tcp:151744:91"/>Prayers for the peaceful re-ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Church and State: by the late Pious and Reverend <hi>H. Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> in 120.</p>
            <p>A Serious and Compaſſionate In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the Cauſes of the preſent Neglect and Contempt of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion and Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Demonſtration of the Divine Authority of the Law of Nature, and of the Chriſtian Religion. In Two Parts: by <hi>Samuel Parker,</hi> D. D. Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon preached before the Judges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the time of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes in the Cathedral Church at <hi>Giouceſter,</hi> on Sunday <hi>Aug.</hi> 7. 1681. Publiſhed to put a ſtop to Falſe and Injurious Repreſentations: by <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Fowler,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>The Primitive Chriſtian Juſtified; or, a Scripture Demonſtration, That to be Innocent and Perſecuted, is more Eligible than to be Proſperouſly Wicked. Delivered in a Sermon in
<pb facs="tcp:151744:91"/>the Abby-Church of <hi>Bath:</hi> by <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Goulde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached before the Lord Mayor and the Court of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, at <hi>Guild-Hall</hi>-Chappel on the <hi>7th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1682. By <hi>Francis Turner,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>The Vindication of Chriſtianity againſt Paganiſm, in <hi>Octavo,</hi> new.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
